To Jesus Christ, glory forever, you're listening to ancient faithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship Him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but...
is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints. In our time, many year into break free
of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is
this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with
spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
young. Post this live Colin show.
focused on enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and
experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, manticore manglers.
Christ has risen, he truly has risen.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast, my co-host, the very reverend, almost
double doctor, Stephen D. Young, is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
I am Father Andrew Stephen Damien.
almost double master in Emmaus, Pennsylvania, and we are live. And if you are listening to us live,
you can call us at 855-237-2346 and speak with us. And we're going to get your calls in the
second half of the show and our very own most beloved, Montesca Trudy will be taking your calls.
And we are both checking in safe from Kendrick Lamar diss tracks.
He's a savage.
So far he's left us alone.
So far. So last time we talked about the testaments of the 12 patriarchs beginning our series on apocryphal literature from the period of Second Temple Judaism.
Tonight we're going to be talking about the book of Jubiles, which is probably my favorite text of this sort.
I think it's the most accessible of all of these books, requiring the least background
knowledge to get what's going on in the text, unlike books such as First Enoch, which we'll
talk about that is.
some point, you know, on this podcast.
If you know Genesis, and at least the beginning of Exodus,
then you have the framework that you need for this text
for Jubilee.
So, but nonetheless, it's still kind of a bit different
among all the apocrypha related to the Old Testament.
So, why is that?
Why is this one different from the rest of those?
Different title.
Oh, there you go.
This one's called the Book of Jubilee.
The other ones are called other stuff, you know.
to read titles.
First Dean Eckert.
I was trying to remember when Jubilee
was first introduced in the X-Men,
and my memory is failing me now,
but I feel like it was in the night.
So that would have been,
it's either 1989 or 1990.
It was actually an off issue.
It's when the X-Men were in Australia.
It was the Australian team.
After the fall of the mutants.
and
There were four female members and four male members and the four female members went to a mall in Australia
And they made the Jubilee May 1989 on Kenny X-Men
1944 I think it was about 1989 and
Yeah, 244 and
Then she ended up kind of hanging around people didn't realize she was hanging around in what had been the Revers base in
And the Australian outback and so then when
Wolverine nearly got killed by the Revers in issue 251. She came and rescued him and then sort of became his sidekick for a while
That I remember
Man that was a long time ago
We were just starting high school as I recall that that was like right at the transition from Mark Silvestre
Penciling it to Jim Lee. Yeah, which is before Jim Lee got really big. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah
And in the middle of Chris Claremont's like 17 year run riding
I'm kidding, I'm kidding, I'm kidding, I'm kidding.
Right. And so tonight we're going to be talking about a second temple Jewish text dedicated. Yeah, that is not related to that at all.
Exactly. In no way. Right.
Like her name just comes for the fact that her given name is jubilation Lee. Right. Right. It's just a nickname. Yeah. And so it's like shortened.
Yeah, but we couldn't we couldn't not reference her at some point in this episode. So yeah, so might as well get it over with. Yeah. Yeah.
So all right. So why else is the book of Jubilee is different from the other second temple Jewish literature?
Oh, aside from the title. Yes. That would be the contents are different. Oh. Anyway.
Yeah, no more what we were getting at in terms of I mean that's how they're all different from each other. But now
So the uniqueness is sort of the legacy of the history that the text
of the Book of Jubiles has had. So last time we were talking about the testaments of the 12
Patriarchs and the testaments of the 12 Patriarchs is kind of typical for a lot of these that we're
going to be talking about in that the text was preserved among Christians and not among
and rabbinic Jewish groups.
So like we talked about last.
time testaments of 12 patriarchs we have from basically two places the Dead Sea
scrolls which is of course a pre-Christian Jewish community and then Christian
monasteries right and the monasteries are where it was preserved because a number of
these texts and the reason for that is that many if not most of these texts
that were made use of by the early Christians or
come from Jewish communities that ended up developing into Christian communities
were if they had a lot of currency in other Jewish groups and especially in
fair-sake Judaism, they tended to be then rejected because they were seen as
being Christian. Christians were pointing to them and using them to show the
antiquity of their own beliefs.
And so, because when you get to the point where rabbinic Jewish communities are declaring
Christian communities are radical, they're also going to declare the communities that produce
those texts the Christians were using heretical.
Yeah, and I mean, this is not some weird, crazy thing, right?
If you remember what first century Judaism is like, it's not this single religious group
that believes exactly one list of things and has exactly one list of texts.
There's a variety there.
you know as we...
right, or Judaism's. Right. And just as Christianity kind of took one track and said, okay,
no, this, this viewpoint, this set of interpretations is the true Judaism, so to speak.
Rebindic Judaism took, you know, another, another turn and ruled out, you know, various other things.
Right. And then because of the political realities of Rebindic Judaism and Christianity developing in
parallel there was more of an onus
for one side to condemn the other and fight about it than there was in the diverse pre-Christian
Judaism, where sort of just different Jews and different parts of the world were doing
their thing in their communities, right? Nobody was super worried about it. But there were
any number of other political realities, especially those caused by the Roman Empire that
caused it to be a critical issue for the two groups to want to distinguish themselves.
from each other. But so that's sort of the normal thing. That's what you expect.
That's what you're going to find with first-seeing, and second-eeneck. Any number of
other texts that we're going to end up talking about the show, but that's not what
you actually find with the Book of Jubiles. And so first of all you find the
book of Jubilee is being used across a wise swath of Jewish groups and
parts of the world already in the Second Temple period, in the pre-Christian period.
So it's not just a question of, even though technically, because of certain things in it,
Jubilee's might be considered part of the Anarchic literature, the book of First
Enic, for example, is intensely popular among certain groups, certain sects, certain communities,
Second-second-table Judaism.
and either unknown or rejected across a swath of other communities.
Right.
So the Pharisees, for example, in some case, the reason I want to specify unknown or rejected
is that it's not the case that, for example, the Pharisees, and it's really out of the Pharisees
that rabbinic Judaism comes.
Right.
It's not that they rejected all of these books, or that they had previously accepted all
all these books and...
and then later rejected them. A lot of them, they just didn't use. They didn't have any
tradition of using them. Right. They just were never in there. Yeah. They were never
in. They didn't get taken out. They were never in. Right. The rabbinic Jewish Old Testament
Canon is basically other than a couple of books on the edges is basically the Pharisee at
Canon. But the Pharisees always considered to be authoritative, for example. Right. Yeah.
You
Even though they never seem to consider canonical the same way, the book of Jubilee's was used
to refer to among the Pharisees and sort of exhibit A of that as Josephus in his antiquities
when he's going through the history, right?
He's writing a work of history, history of the Jewish people for a Roman audience.
And so when he's going through the events in the Book of Genesis,
He's very clearly working from the Book of Jubiles on any number of counts, right?
He's got all kinds of content in there that's clearly coming from the Book of Jubiles and
not Genesis itself.
And he's a Pharisee, right?
And we also, as I mentioned, you could consider because the contents to be anachic literature,
also.
find it with other inocic literature in other Jewish communities. So it crossed over between
these groups. But that fairisaic relationship with the text where it's not canonical, but it's
kind of the way we've talked about Christian apocrypha functioning. It's a book that's worth being
read, but isn't read publicly. That has been maintained in rabbinic Judaism. That has been
and maintain the rabbinic Judaism.
If you go to any of the, there are online websites that are sort of the Jewish equivalent
of Bible Hub or Bible Gateway or Blue Letter Bible for Christians.
But there are Jewish versions of that that have, you know, the texts of the Hebrew Bible
and different Revenant commentaries and that kind of thing, all cross-reference and available
there.
If you go there, sometimes you have to dig around a little.
But if you go to any of...
those, you will eventually find the Book of Jubilee's on there. It'll be there somewhere.
Does that mean the average Jewish person you meet, even if they attended Orthodox synagogue?
We'll know all about the Book of Jubilee's, no. Right. Right. Just like, you know, we talked
last time about the test for the 12 patriarchs and how it's on Mount Athos and all this, but
if you ask the average Orthodox person about it, they won't know much about it. Right.
Yeah, so that's what that's what I mean also
when I say it functions in kind of the same way.
Historically it has functioned that way.
In modern times, maybe it's fallen into a lack of knowledge.
And the comments you will find on those websites,
or if you talk to somebody, a Jewish person
who knows their stuff, they will say
that the book of Jubilee's is not canonical,
but it contains important historical information.
Hmm, or it's historically accurate.
it. Now, later on tonight, when we talk about some of the contents, that's going to make
you wonder because some fun stuff in there. There's a lot of stuff in there that is not
accepted by Orthodox Judaism today in the contents. But that's probably why they
Preface it with the not canonical part.
Because there are parts that they accepted parts, maybe.
Not so much, but that's pretty unique. There aren't any other to my knowledge that I've
been able to find, any other second-templed Jewish texts of these kind of texts that are
still current in rabbinic Judaism in the same way. There are elements of lots of things.
There are elements of early midrash itself that were incorporated into the Talmud and then
through the Talmud.
still have currency and rabbinic Judaism. But there's not a text like this still in its original
second temple form that still functions this way. Yeah. In, in, in rabbinic Judaism. So that's unique.
right and so that also means that at the point where we have these two
community.
that are slowly separating, getting more and more separate,
more and more opposition even is taking place.
The rabbinic Jewish communities and Christian communities
that are separating out of Second Temple Judaism,
that the Book of Jubiles is being used by both.
The Book of Jubiles, even though, right,
right, not given canonical public reading status for the
most part in either of them still holds some currency, is still functioning as
apocrypha, is still functioning as this book worth reading in both of those
sets of communities, which again is really unique for any of these tax.
Yeah. And kind of interesting and like I thought about this since we since
you and I talked about this and I thought like well why what is it about this book?
I don't know. I mean, we could speculate, but I don't know that there's a clear answer to that.
Yeah, I think we're going to get into that a little here.
At least, I think some of the things we're going to talk about here in this first half.
If you put a number of them together, I think they help point to why.
But some of them also point away from it.
So as I mentioned, technically speaking,
the book of Jubilee's would be classified with an archipelago literature. While it had this
relationship with Pharisees and that's unique, it was very prominent in any community where the
the inocularity is prominent.
Yeah, so like cummeron, the Dead Sea Scrolls people.
Yeah.
And it's the reason we say it's part of the inocularity
is not just...
sort of that association, right?
Because like, yeah, Isaiah's in the Densy scrolls too.
Right?
That's not an archic literature.
It's a couple of things.
First is that it's a text that's in the apocalyptic genre.
And it's apocalyptic, it's an apocalypse
in the sense that we've talked about before on the show.
Right?
We have apocalypse in our head, meaning the end of the world.
Yeah.
Which is actually completely wrong.
for God.
Apocalypse means revelation, something being revealed.
And as we've talked about before, apocalyptic literature presents a situation
usually some kind of heavenly journey.
Someone enters into the heavenly realm.
And based on having entered into the heavenly realm, they have a new perspective
on the world, on its history,
Yes, on certain future events, but...
on sort of the whole sweep of human history,
what's going on in the world,
and that unique perspective allows them to flesh out
in particular what is going on spiritually
behind various events.
Yeah, it's sort of the heaven's eye view.
So there are things going on that we can all see
and experience, right?
But then there's also spiritual realities behind that
that may not always be.
as a parent to us, especially when we're going through whatever the situation is,
the person who has sort of exited time as we're experiencing it and sees it for this other
perspective can then fill in the rest of that vision for us. And so this is very much what happens
in the book of Jubilee's, it's just mostly framed as history, right? So the
central figure is Moses in the book of Jubilee's and he is seeing history up to
his time. So sort of Genesis 1, 1 through Moses being up on Mount Sinai. And he's
seeing that from that heavenly perspective. Now that said, though it's a vision of
the past history, another part of what happens in apocalyptic literature is
Is that a Paco?
limited literature provided a way to speak about the present in a kind of coded way. So in this case,
you're speaking about the past, right? And we'll see this in the book of Enic and other
anarchic literature. You're talking about the past, you're talking about like the days of Noah,
or you're talking about the days of the patriarchs, but you're really talking about the present.
Yeah, you're talking.
about because you're making sort of direct, sometimes not subtle comparisons between things
that happened in the past and the spiritual reality behind them and things that are going
on now and the spiritual reality behind them.
And really that's the intent of the communication.
This is important when you're reading, say, the apocalypse of St. John, the book of Revelation
in the Bible that St John is really writing about things that were
going on then. People then let the reader understand as he keeps saying. But by talking about
these spiritual realities in general or in terms of things that happened in the past like
the birth of Christ, that was the past from his perspective. But then through that, talk
about now through this comparison. We'll see some more examples of that as we go on.
And then a special
sort of blatantly in your face obvious in the Book of Jubilies in terms of it being
anachic literature is almost constant apologetics for the anachic calendar. When we eventually
talk about the Book of Enic, we'll go into some detail on the anachic calendar because
there's a big section of the Book of Enic that is just laying out that calendar. But
The Inocket calendar was a 364 day calendar.
that had four sets of three 30-day months with a sort of interstitial day between them.
So you have four 90-day periods, three months each, that give you 360 days.
And then you had four more days that were each one day was stuck in between each group of three months each group of 90 days
It's like a Shire calendar.
And what the Adakit calendar did for you, they considered it to be mathematically perfect
because, for example, all the Jewish restays fell on them, not only the same date but the
same day of the week every year.
And so everything sort of lined up as far as they were concerned.
That meant it was mathematically perfect.
That meant it was God's calendar.
There's the regular Jewish calendar that the Pharisees use.
For example, you have to add a whole month every few years to get it back.
Me, truth. Yeah, because it's a lunar calendar, right?
So you have to add like you trucks today.
So they're like, well, look, see, obviously that's a bogus calendar.
That's a man-made calendar because it's not perfect. It's not mathematically perfect.
If it came from God, it would be perfect.
It wasn't in use long enough as far as we could tell for anyone to notice that it wasn't perfect either.
Yeah.
But it was only a day and a quarter and a couple of hours off.
So it would have taken longer to notice.
But so that, in these communities, again, we want to...
We tend to treat these texts as sort of these free-floating things,
but they weren't. They were deeply connected to the lives of communities.
And so this calendar
issue, this calendar thing was really the central issues for most enochic communities.
Like Kumran, they went out in the desert and left the temple in Jerusalem, and society
was the best because of this calendar issue.
Yeah, because this is about how you live your life day to day, I mean, it shapes your
actual real life.
Right.
So this is what it was really about.
It was about the way...
the community's life and the rhythms of the community's life and the patterns of the community's life.
And these texts were embraced because these texts laid out, explained, argued for,
defended that way of life. Right? Here's signified by the calendar.
This is again, why it's so interesting that in Ferris Aiken, Rubenic Judaism,
The lack of Jubilee's had any.
currency, because it's so blatantly argues we're a calendar that they did not use.
And we'll see some actual examples of that as we go forward.
In terms of understanding the text, right, so the sort of shape of the text of the Book
of Jubilee's is very different than like the Testament of the 12 Patriots.
Yeah.
last time, or a lot of them that we're going to read in the future, like the ascension of Isaiah.
Right. Or the Book of Enic. Yeah. I mean, probably the biggest, most obvious difference is that
Jubilee's is basically just narrative. Right. Just simply telling a story. Right. Right. And the,
you know, when you read, when we talk about the test of the 12 patriarchs, right,
This is an incident that's not recorded in the Bible.
Right, right, the deaths of the 12 sons of Jacob are not recorded.
In the Bible, whatever their last words were is not recorded.
Right, so this is completely composed.
Right, this is just, I'm going to write this thing and I'm going to communicate certain things
through the mouth of this biblical character.
We saw that that had reference if there was much information about them in the Bible
That was sort of incorporated or used as a jumping off point.
But really, this was a whole new story, or the ascension of Isaiah talking about Isaiah's
martyrdom, that's not recorded in the Old Testament at all.
Yeah.
Right.
So this is just a sort of nude, even though it's a narrative, it's like a new narrative,
right?
It's a, right.
Whereas Jubilee is basically takes Genesis and a little bit of the beginning of Exodus
and tells the same story with a lot of the same detail.
honestly. Yeah. But kind of expands on certain parts and it's commenting on it. Right.
Right. And this is a mode of commenting on the text that was very common in second
temple and later rabbinic Judaism. So this is one of the things that might explain why this is a text
that maybe you had a little more currency in rabbinic Judaism in that
there are texts sort of like this or formatted like this within rabbinic Judaism.
So for example, you've got the Targumim, the Targums, right?
We've talked about it various points on the show, the Aramaic Targum, Targum just means translation.
But the Aramaic Targums are what's usually referred to, and people just refer to the Targums.
and these are Aramaic translations.
of the Hebrew Bible, various parts of the Hebrew Bible.
But not like word-for-word or thought-for-thought translations.
Right.
In many cases, yeah.
Yeah, there's a little bit of explanation
or other comments included.
So what's understood here by translation, yeah.
So we today, our modern idea of translation is
you're either trying to go as Father Andrew said,
you're trying to go word-for-word.
Like okay, so here's this.
I
I'm going to translate the New Testament into English for the 50,000th time for some reason.
So I see this Greek word.
I am going to figure out what English word is relatively similar in meaning to this
Greek word, and I will write that English word.
And then, depending on your translation strategy, you smooth that out.
little or a lot for an English reader once you have a whole sentence. Right. Or, as
Father Andrew said, the other very common, a modern approach is thought for thought where
you say, well, we can't do it word for word because Greek syntax and grammar is totally
different than English syntax and grammar. Right. So sometimes there's going to be one
Greek word and we're going to need three or four English words to really convey the meaning.
Right, like...
It's a future perfect, right? So I have to say he will have had gone.
Right. Whereas in Greek, that'll just be the ending of a verb. Yeah, yeah. And that'll just be one word in Greek.
Right. So, right. So you say, okay, well, we're just going to try the thoughts, the ideas. Right. We're going to take the idea that the Greek is communicating and communicate that same idea in English.
This ancient mode of translation that produced the Targums is closer to that second one, but goes even further.
Yeah.
Right? Because it not only is sort of like trying to convey the thought and the idea, and will use as many words or even sentences as necessary to try to communicate what they believed the idea of the Hebrew to be.
be with some precision, it would also seek to
answer obvious questions about the text sometimes. Right? So if you read a verse
and after reading it, there's sort of an obvious sort of obvious question about it.
Well wait, what does that mean? Or why did he do that? Right? The translator would
just supply the reason. We just put in there, oh he did this because
a duh. Yeah right. And you get a little bit of the flavor of this. You get a little bit of the
flavor of this actually when you read St. John's Gospel of the New Testament. Oh yeah because he
gives little comments here and there. Yeah he's not translating but he just writes that way.
He just puts in these parenthetical comments. This is sort of a very Jewish mode of writing at
at this time, right?
And so when you read the Aramaic, it's not.
just that it was a little free with the translation, right? Like you're reading the NIV or something.
It was that, you know, they'd add the never inspired version. That's what I said.
But they'd, you know, add, like in some cases, almost a whole story, you know, like a whole
like explanatory thing.
And so the
the Jewish communities, even the ones where people knew Aramaic and their Hebrew wasn't very good,
so they needed to use these Aramaic Targums a lot. They kind of knew that was going on, right? And so
when you look at the rules for synagogues in the second temple period and around the time of Christ,
you couldn't just go and read a Targum in the synagogue.
If you were going to use the Targum in a synagogue, you had to read the Hebrew.
first, right? You get up and read the Hebrew first and then you could read the
Aramaic for the people there who only knew Aramaic. But because of how Lucy
Gussi it was, they wouldn't let you just read the Targon by itself. You could
read the Greek by itself, by the way. So there was a recognition that the Greek
translate the old Greek and the Septuagint in the case of the Torah.
We're recognized as being, you know, what we would call closer to a word for word kind of thing.
And so it could be read by themselves.
But so people were used to reading, you know, the text of Scripture with some enhancements, with some explanatory notes that weren't in footnotes or margins that were just in there in the text.
Just added in.
And there was not a sense of like they're pulling a fast one.
Right.
And then you get the midrasheme, which go even further than that.
Midrash.
Midrash is basically a method of commentary, where you would have the actual text of Scripture,
but then copious amounts of explanatory material.
Again, not in a footnote or a margin note, but just put in there with the text.
Um.
So a good example of something from the midrash that St. Paul actually refers to.
St. Paul, in first Corinthians, is talking about, he's sort of going through in an analogical way the history of Israel in the wilderness and making a comparison to Christians living in the world.
of the world. And so he talks about how all of these rides passed
through the sea and passed through the cloud and they were baptized in Moses, right?
And he says, and Israel had a rock that followed them in the wilderness and that rock was
Christ. And we go, Oh, yeah, the rock, you know, Moses hated it, gave water, right?
The rock is Christ. Cool. And we skip right over that followed them part. Yeah. Right?
That the rock was following them around. You're not going to find that anywhere in the book
of Exodus.
Yep.
But it comes from the answer to a question.
At the beginning of their 40 years of wandering in the desert,
they get water from that rock.
At the end of their 40 years wandering in the desert, there's another rock that Moses hits that he's not supposed to.
And they get water from that rock.
Where do they get water for the rest of the 40 years?
Right? The manna was falling wherever they were, but where did their water come from?
Right?
And so the answer that you get when you read
midrashim about the rock is that well the rock followed them yeah the whole
time yeah and not just like a little note oh by the way the rock followed them
what you find in the midrash is not only a whole story about the rock following
them but the complete text of a song that Israel sang every time
made camp to get the rock to pick up from where it was and to roll over to them and deposit
itself where they were camped now.
That's so amazing.
And all the rejoicing they did every time it happened.
So it's like this whole developed story, right?
But it's just incorporated into the text.
I believe it's at the midrash on numbers.
So again, this is a thing, right?
Interest team are still be-
used in rabbinic Judaism. And so again, this was just a way of, oh yeah, this is, we're accepting.
This other stuff isn't on the same level as the Hebrew text of the Torah itself, but there's,
this other information. And by the way, Saint Paul feels totally free to just reference these
traditions. He doesn't feel the need to parodedically say, oh, but that whole following
thing.
That's just a tradition. That's not actually in the Bible. Yeah, he just says the rock was Christ. He just says yeah
There was a rock that followed them. Everybody knows that
By the way the magicians were named Janice and Janvars. He says later on. Yeah
Yeah
It's almost like he didn't believe in solacecriptor or something
But so that's it exalt the kinds of stories right that you get so
So there are other...
forms of rabbinic literature,
dealing with and commenting on the text
that follow that kind of format,
which is also kind of the way Jubilee's is written,
which is different from the way
most apocalyptic literature and most inoclic literature is written.
And so this is, I think, one of the reasons why it might
have had more currency with that community
in that they kind of had a box to put it in, right?
Oh, this is interpretations
and the traditions associated with.
with the book of Genesis. Right, this is sort of a midrash on Genesis. Right, this is a
sort of weird talk of Genesis. There's some weird stuff in there. Yeah. There's plenty of wild stuff in the midrash though.
So I mean, the kind of things in there pretty well. But so that said that is part of how we have to look at the book of Jubilee.
the book of Jubilee.
because of, because that's how it's written.
So, what that, what I mean by that and what that means is,
when we're talking about, again, we'll look at the testament of the 12-patrex
that we talked about last time, the testaments.
Each of those is a composition, right?
We talked about how at least several of them definitely circulated on their own.
So, this is a composition. It's composed by somebody, it has a theme,
it has a message, right, or a set of messages around a theme.
composed at one point. Whereas, when we're looking at the book of Jubiles and we're sort
of tracking through Genesis and then there are these sort of added details and added bits,
right? We shouldn't assume that there's one person who sat down to write the book of Jubiles
and came up with all of those added bits.
out of his own head. Right? Yeah. Because that's not how that kind of commentary was written.
Right. Rather, the person who's finally putting together what we now call the Book of Jubiles
has all of these bits of tradition and interpretation already, has received them from somewhere.
Right. There may be some of it that's his own thinking, but a lot of it at least, the majority of it
at least.
is stuff that he's received, probably orally.
Maybe some of it textually, or text we don't have anymore,
maybe from other bits and bobs of inoclic literature
that already existed.
But that stuff is all finding a resting place
here in the Book of Jubiles.
So it's a repository of all these different bits
of tradition and interpretation.
Yeah.
And it's important that we set that out because we're going to talk about later on places where things from the book of Jubilee show up in the New Testament.
And when they show up in the New Testament, there are sometimes where it's like virtually a quote.
Yeah, yeah.
Those places look like places where it's the Book of Jubiles.
There are other places where there are just references to things that are in the Book of
Jubiles.
where we can't be sure if, oh, the author is taking this from the book of Jubilies, or if it's just,
you know, this is a Jewish tradition of interpretation that lots of people had.
The earliest written source we have, we have it in, that we today have it in, is the book of
Jubilies. But I mean, it may have been much older than that. It may have been in all kinds of
other literature that we don't have anymore. Yeah. I think, you know, for people maybe
building.
get some sense of this, if people know about the tradition of Arthurian literature, I
mean a big difference, of course, is there is no as far as we know original Arthur story
that we can all point to, unlike that there is Genesis.
But for instance, you get Thomas Mallory, who he writes more D'Arthur, right?
Well, what he's doing is he's compiling a whole bunch of other Arthur stories that he's
gotten from various sources.
You know, so you can see.
these things combined together and he did some editing. It's pretty clear that he did some editing
to make it kind of fit together in certain ways but probably none of it did he actually compose
himself in the sense of coming up with a story. Almost all of it we can point at other sources and say
it's probably from this. Whereas with Jubilee's it's so old that we just don't, if there are other
textual sources, we don't have them, largely speaking.
Probably.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
A lot of probably in this point in history. Well, yeah, about 10. Yeah.
The reason the reason I said probably is for example, right like
Obviously the 364 day a docket calendar that Jubilee's points to pre-existed it. Right? Yes, like course for it because
The book of Enic was written before the book of Jubilee's
And it's laid out in the book of Enic, right?
But we can't say for certain that oh the book of Jubilee's got this from the book of first enek as we have it today
Yeah
Right, it could be both be drawing on something else that we don't have
Right, there's all kinds of different options, right
And I know I'm kind of belaboring this right, but the reason I belabor this is
is one of my pet peeves is
Again, anyone who listens to this show for a long time,
here's me rant all the time about how people need to take logic courses
before they get PhDs.
But people argue all the time, right?
What is essentially a kind of bad scholarly post-hoc or go-proctor-hoc,
right? The argument that, well, x is
existed before why, therefore why plagiarize stole from copied X?
Yeah. Right. Um, there go propped our
hack. Yeah. That's, yes. Whereas no.
Doesn't prove anything. Right. Right. Right. Um,
you know, Doom Patrol and X-Men were developed at the same time.
You can't prove either of them stole-
the other. What early do patrols definitely swiping from the Fantastic Four? They're drawing
some similar traditions. So you have to be much more careful and much more nuanced than that.
Right. Just the fact that something pre-existed something else does not mean that they had any
relationship whatsoever. Yeah. Right. And the the
Especially what we're talking about history, the historical documents.
I don't even say ancient texts, just the historical documents that are
extant today are a tiny fraction of all of the documents that have ever existed.
Oh, yeah.
Right.
And so basing conclusions on making sweeping statements, right.
No one in the early church did this.
Everyone in the early church thought this, right?
All of these statements are ridiculous.
Okay, because we don't have the voices of
anything but a tiny fraction of the people in the early church, a tiny fraction of the bishops
of the early church. Yeah. I mean, it's similar to when people will sometimes say things like
the church fathers say or not. My favorite is none of the church fathers say. I'm like, hold on,
Hold on, hold on.
Number one, can you read all of the languages that would...
be required to literally read all the church fathers. You know, and if it's like
Yoroslav Pelican, okay, yes, this guy reads all those languages. Yeah. But he's
smart enough to say no extent writings of the church fathers say right. Right. Yeah. Yeah.
Right. So you know most of them are not extent. Right. That's why you had to more often say,
I'm not aware of, you know, or something like this church father says.
this in this text. So if I seem to be
belaboring these things sometimes or
sound like I'm being merely mouthed about
things like well we don't know for sure
it could be the good I'm trying to be
responsible. I'm trying to model good
behavior. A little intellectual humility.
To my brethren who you can't model
humility as soon as you set out to do
that you failed but
I tried to model logic right of
Right.
not jumping to conclusions, right?
What can we say for sure?
What can we say probably?
What can we say maybe, right?
It'd be consistent about that, it'd fair about that.
So again, we know that the Book of Jubiles
is a repository for all of these traditions
surrounding the Book of Genesis.
We know it is probably not the origin of most of them,
but a repository of them.
And in many cases, it is our earliest written text
that contain some of those.
additions. All of those are fair statements. So we've been talking about when it was written
and things written before and things written after it. The book of Jubilee's was written
in the mid-second century BC, which is circa 150 BC is what that means. And that puts it
in the time period the Hasmonian era.
immediately after the Maca-Bian revolt to sort of frame it historically.
And there are things in the contents that reveal that pretty clearly.
Even if we weren't just going based on the manuscripts that we have,
manuscript evidence. For example, there is a very obvious shot at the Greeks
Ah, yeah.
In all places the story of the expulsion from Paradise.
There's a comment about Adam receiving the garments of skin, right, to cover his shame
and it says, unlike those who go about naked with unconcealed shame, right, referring to
the gymnasia that...
The Greeks built it in around Judea. Yeah, where people were naked. Yes, that's that's what gymnasia means
Yes
It's naked place
So yeah, yeah, literally when you go to the gym next time boys and girls and you will get thrown out
Yes, don't ask me how I know anyway. Of course in Europe. That's just the word for high school
yeah
so
but
but they did.
that it came for a very literal thing that they exercised in the
but so that's a deliberate shot. Right and that was to carefully give a
little background on that. That was one of the issues preceding the Mac
Abbey and revolt is there were Jewish men who had concocted various means to
try to reverse or hide their circumcision.
Wow.
Because of that. Yeah
Yeah, so that they could go to the gymnasia and
Look like not be obviously Jewish and so
There was a whole idea of being ashamed to be Jewish and this kind of thing
Associated with the gymnasia. So that's why you would get sort of this right seemingly random shot
right? You're talking about the expulsion from paradise and Adam.
and all of a sudden you're like, yeah,
run around naked, shameless, you know.
But that's why, right?
Because it's coming from this time period
and taking a shot at the Greeks.
The earliest copies we have are fragmentary.
They're not the whole text,
but they're in Hebrew and Aramaic
and come from the Dead Sea Scrolls.
Hebrew is clearly the original language. We have enough of the Hebrew and enough of other languages to be able to determine that.
Pretty accurately. We have a lot of, even though they're fragmentary, we have a lot of copies among the Densey Scrolls. It is the third most common text among the Densey Scrolls, in terms of number of copies there.
And in general, because of the time and expense and effort that was required to copy a manuscript.
when you're looking at a library, like an ancient library,
whether it's at a monastery or like at Comron or that kind of thing,
the more copies of a text you find, generally it's considered the more important
that text was, because the more effort and time and expense they were putting
into preserving that particular text as opposed to others.
And the three most common texts for the record in the Dead Sea Scrolls.
Number one is the Book of Genesis.
Number two is the Book of Enec at number three.
is the Book of Jubilies. Most of the text is available in a Latin translation.
And here's what this is also definitely a unique thing among Second Temple Jewish texts.
You can reconstruct almost the entire Greek text from patristic citations.
You can take quotes from the Churchwathers and construct
almost the entire book of Jubilee's in Greek.
Yeah, which I think the only other text you can do that
with is probably portions of the Bible.
Right.
Right. Yeah.
So yeah, you can't do that with any of the other
second-templarature texts that we're gonna talk about.
Yeah, which another is another way of kind of showing
how popular this text.
was. Right, and that's in Christian, in a Christian context, right, of the Churchwaters.
And of course, we have the entire text in Geaz and there it's called, it's titled The Book of
Divisions, Like the New Champions of Time. And everybody, that's the liturgical language of the
Ethiopians. Yes. And that's because it was publicly read by Ethiopian Jews.
the pre-Christian period, and then Ethiopian Christians took over the Ethiopian
Jewish canon as their Old Testament. That's why we have the whole text in that
language. So this means the fact that we have all that, you know, we talked about
with, since it's the other one we talked about, I wouldn't keep using it for
comparisons, the testaments of the 12th patriarchs, we talked about how we have
Some of them in Aramaic, all of them in Greek,
how there are differences between the Aramaic and Greek.
This amount of testimony to the text
in this many different language sources
is kind of unprecedented for any of these texts,
which is another testament to the popularity,
across a range of different people,
across a range of centuries.
And so, but having all those different translations,
We have a really good idea of what the text is.
Yeah, the original, you can really reconstruct well what the original must have been.
Right.
Even though we've got a lot of these texts are fragmentary and we're talking about most,
and almost the entire text, right, we've got so many different witnesses and different languages that we can pinpoint,
you know, what the text says, really, really well.
That's unusual.
A lot of these texts, there are multiple versions and multiple languages.
as we saw last time as we'll see in the future.
talking about these texts. So the basic overview of the structure and when we get into our second half
we're going to go into much more detail about the structure. But basically the structure
of the book of Jubilee is that there's sort of this frame story and the frame story is Moses
on Mount Sinai. Moses on the top of Mount Sinai. Yeah, which, you know, that's in Exodus,
That's right.
you get Moses on Sinai and we know that Moses has given the Torah on Sinai, but you don't
like that's never sort of plays out on camera so to speak in the scriptures.
Right. You know what I mean?
And when we say Torah here we're saying Torah like the book of Genesis, right?
Right. It's part of the Torah.
Right. So this is, you know, Jubilee's is sort of saying, now what if you could have been there?
right? As Moses is getting this vision and you saw it with
them, and then it plays out.
So the body of the text within the frame story is a retelling of the book of Genesis.
But it sort of begins and ends, the frame, the narrative frame, begins and ends with Moses
on Mount Sinai.
And so that does mean that the contents of the book of Genesis are being framed as a vision
that Moses is receiving.
So
that's being revealed to Moses, right? Meaning the story of the creation of the world, the expulsion
from paradise, snow in the flood, the Tower of Babel. These aren't like traditions that were
handed down to Moses. This isn't Moses rewriting those stories as they were told by the other nations.
This is a Moses communicating certain theological ideas that he received from God.
This is Moses recounting this vision he received of these things
According to the book of Jubiles, right?
That's how the book of Jubiles is presenting it
He's sort of seeing this play out and then he's recording it
Right that doesn't mean that the book of Jubiles is presenting this all as quote-unquote literal modern history
Right no because it's being presented as a vision that opens up all these
different levels of interpretation, right, of interpreting Moses' vision.
What this also means though about the text because of the way the text is written,
that because this is sort of a recap or retelling of Genesis,
part of what's being communicated by the text, part of the way in which the text communicates,
is based on what within the text is moved over quickly
and what within the task.
is expanded upon. Right? So the text is free to add in stories, add in information, add in details,
right? Flesh out things that are only briefly discussed in Genesis and they're a place where it
does this. And so if we have a place where one or two verses in Genesis becomes two three chapters
in Jubilee's, right? Well, obviously this is the author of Jubilee's thought this part was very
important.
Right.
If we have something that's three verses in Genesis and is also three verses in Jubilee's or even gets skipped over
in Jubilee's in the retelling, then that's something that the author of Jubilee's didn't think was as important.
Right? To touch on again and comment on. Right?
So just that emphasis or lack of emphasis is part of how the book of Jum-
who these communicates.
Part of what the author is telling us is,
what episodes in Genesis, what stories,
what figures in Genesis he thinks are really key
and important and wants to focus on.
Yeah, and I think it's worth pointing out,
like this is not intended to be a replacement
for the book of Genesis.
No.
Right, it's a commentary of sorts.
So it's not like you're saying, well these parts don't...
matter so I'm not going to include them in my version of the story. You know, it's just
like, you know, just like listening to Father Stevens Bible study in a case you just sort of
reads through a genealogy. Some genealogies, he reads through, he points out, well, a bunch of
stuff for an hour, but others you're like, and bigot, bigot, bigot, bigot, okay, next.
Yeah. Yeah. Sometimes you just have more to say about this than about that, right?
right but this is
This is true of all authors.
Any author you read who's writing secondary literature.
And this is secondary literature.
Jubilee is a secondary literature. It's commenting on Genesis.
Anyone writing secondary literature, that includes all history writing, for example.
Do you have to make choices?
Right, you don't end up focusing on every figure and every event.
and every line of text to the same degree.
And if you do, your work becomes very tiresome.
It's hard to read.
You always make choices, right?
And so part of reading and understanding a text,
a secondary text, is understanding and identifying those choices that were made.
and what the author is doing.
and how he's communicating by way of those choices.
So this isn't something weird that Jubilee's does.
This is something that everybody writing secondary literature does.
Yep.
Right.
And then sort of a last note, because we can pretty much reconstruct, we have a lot of
the Hebrew text firsthand from the other language versions, we can reconstruct the rest.
This is just kind of an interesting tidbit that...
The Hebrew text that Jubilee's is working from and commenting on, right?
Because it's just quoting it a lot of the time.
Doesn't quite match any Hebrew text that we're aware of.
It doesn't really match the proto-maceretic text.
I won't go too far down that rabbit hole, but technically the
Maseritic text didn't exist in the second century BC,
because the mass...
who it's named after, the scribes who it's named after,
didn't exist for hundreds of years afterward.
And what makes it the Maseratic text is their notes.
So, but the text they would later put their notes on,
did exist in the second century BC, and it's not that.
So, it's not the Hebrew text that's commonly used by rabbinic Judaism today
or that's used for Protestant
testaments, it's also not the Hebrew text that underlies the Greek translations
because there's a different Hebrew text. And this is part of what we have to
remember that in the second century BC still the Hebrew text was not settled.
The Hebrew text was fluid and there were a number of different Hebrew textual
traditions at that time. So for example
the book of Jeremiah is much longer in the Hebrew text, in the Maseratic text, than it is in the Greek version.
At Kumaran, in the Dead Sea Scrolls, we found Hebrew copies of the long version and the short version of the book of Jeremiah.
A Hebrew text that matches the Greek text and a Hebrew text that matches the Greek text.
as the later Hebrew text. Side by side, the same community had both of them. So there was not a
single canonical text at this point, even in Hebrew. There are variations at this point.
And so whatever text the author of Jubilee's is using, it's not identical to either of those.
So there's another Hebrew textual tradition now law.
out there that Jubilee is using.
Cool. Yeah. So it's valuable for biblical scholarship in and of itself, even apart from the
sort of commentary side. Old Testament textual criticism. Yeah.
Interesting world. Exactly. Yes, it is. I've been reading some more of that stuff lately.
It gets weirder the deeper you go. All right. Well, that's our first half on this episode on the
the book of Jubilee's will be right back with the second-
and half of this episode of The Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of The Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Ancient Faith Radio is brought to you by our listeners
with help from Byzantine coffee.
Enjoy a great...
of Byzantine coffee while tithing to your parish. A non-profit organization, Byzantine coffee is
the product of prayer, reflection, and the work of a few Orthodox Christians. When purchasing our
small family co-ops sourced and air-roasted coffees, add your parish discount code at checkout
to tithe 10% of your purchase price. We also offer a fine grind for your Greek or Arabic coffees.
Subscribe and save 5% on every purchase.
Visit us at Byzantine.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back.
I have a question.
You have a question.
Yes.
Byzantine coffee.
and cocked elaborate schemes to assassinate you and make itself the emperor?
Well that is what Harnack said.
Yeah.
Just curious.
I mean I could be down for that on a boring Saturday.
That could add some intrigue.
Actually, I'll pay extra if my coffee can do that.
Yeah.
Yes, assassins grind.
So yes, we're talking about the book of Jubilee's and getting a lot of great
engagement on on the YouTube's from some of our commenters there. So hello YouTube. We're very happy to have you with us this evening or morning for those of you over in East Asia, which some of you are.
Do you mean they're fighting you or?
No, not that kind of engagement. Yes, yes.
Yeah, so we're talking about the book of Jubilee as we just discussed basically what it is, right?
Kind of in a meta sense and its place and in
Jewish and Christian history early on, why it was being read and continued to be read
by both Jews and Christians even up until this very day. So yeah, so the second part of
this episode, we're going to be discussing sort of the structure of the book.
What's... Well, the first part of the second part. Yes, first part of the...
That's true, yes. The structure of it.
today's episode is uh
constructed after Thomas Aquinas's sumo theologica.
Yes.
There's a first part, a first part of the second part,
a second part of the second part, and then a third part.
And a third part of the fifth part with, yeah.
But not four halves.
No, just three halves.
We've only ever had one episode with four halves.
Yes.
That was the Thunder Gods episode, if I remember correctly.
Which was two two two shows in one.
Indeed.
So.
Yeah, so...
structure is actually a theme of the book. Like it's not just we're talking about that this book has structure.
Structure is part of book of divisions. Yeah, the book of divisions is the literal name of it. Yeah.
Which a Jubilee is a division from the Old Testament.
Division of time. Yeah. Yeah, division of time. Yeah. Yeah. So
yeah, so there is
Basically, the entire book is structured around.
The Inakit calendar, therefore around the Jewish Feast, the Festival cycle, the various
other cycles of the calendar, as mapped out on the 364 day Inakit calendar.
Now we're going to get into a little more of what that means, right?
In a little more detail.
So it's centered around the most important feast.
We talked about this a few episodes ago, but if you haven't heard that episode,
you probably wouldn't guess which beast it is, right? You might guess,
like, well, Passover, right, or day of atonement, but no.
It's centered around Pentecost, it's centered around the Feast of Weeks.
Yeah.
Which is interesting for a bunch of reasons, but is
the feast that
us
celebrated every year the giving of the Torah Mount Sinai,
which as we said is sort of the frame story,
right for the book.
But that is the central feast.
And Moses, as we talk about the book of Jubilee's
being apocalyptic literature, right?
Apocalyptic literature has someone making this divine ascent.
And so Moses is...
of Sinai in the book of Jubilee is such a divine ascent because he goes to the top and he is now in the presence of God.
So the top of the mountain has become paradise. He has entered into it. He is now in the heavenly realm.
And there, the feast of Pentecost, the feast of the giving of the Torah, of the giving of the covenant, of the ratification of the covenant is an eternal reality.
And that is because God is eternally faithful to loyal to the covenant.
The ratification of the covenant, what we're concretely talking about, the first time it
was done, right, was when the people of Israel said, all these things you have said we
will do, right?
And then they got spattered with blood, right?
I had their fingers crossed we know from the rest of the Hebrew
Yes, but they said all these things you have said we will do, right?
That was them ratifying it, right?
so
God eternally ratifying it means
There's no doubt there's never a question
God is going to honor his covenant
Yeah, right
Terms of blessings, terms of curses, terms of all the things he promised.
note out from his side. Right? And so the Feast of Weeks then, Pentecost was a yearly
representation, reenactment, ritual participation in it from the other side, where the people
again every year, right, through the ritual participation of participating in the Feast of
weeks. Stood at the foot of Mountside.
and I, and said all of these things
that you have commanded we will do.
Yeah, it's, it's, it's,
it's that there's kind of an eternal
pentacost being celebrated in, in heaven.
And once a year, humanity goes and celebrates
with the angels.
Right.
And it's in what, what's ongoing in heaven.
Right. Right.
And so this presents a certain idea
of the relationship between...
eternity and cyclical time
Right and cyclical time
I know you've heard this thing. It's a very modern thing
Right that all the pagans thought that time was cyclical and
The Jews didn't they thought it was linear. Yeah, okay. Yeah
Yeah, it's nonsense.
So there's there's
There's an element of truth to it.
Here's the more accurate statement.
Pagan thought that time was circular.
Circular.
Meaning, still linear.
Everything just happens over and over and over and over again.
All of this has happened before and all of this will happen again.
Yeah.
Universal collapse eventually in destruction and be reborn.
all the gods will come back and they believed the world was eternal.
There's all of these things.
Yes, gods were born and gods died.
Humans were born and humans died.
Civilizations rose and civilizations fell.
Everything just repeated itself over and over again and went nowhere.
Whereas in Scripture, you have this presentation of time and eternity, right?
and time is cyclical which is not the same thing as certain.
Yeah, and like one of the ways that we see this, I mean we mentioned this over and over again on this show this idea of ritual participation bringing us to experience
eternal realities, right, that we keep coming back to them on calendar days, but we're entering into an eternal reality.
Well, this is this is simply illustrated here in Jubilee is this principle that we've been talking about over and over again.
over and over again. And is the reason that so many orthodox hymns begin with the word today, even if they're
talking about an event that from a kind of historical point of view is long in the past.
Right. Right. And so what a calendar does, a liturgical calendar, well any calendar,
what any calendar does, right, because any calendar you use is going to be cyclical.
There will be a series of weeks that make up a series of months, right?
that make up a series of years. That cycle is going to repeat. There's going to be a May 23rd
every year. It loops back around. Even if you want to talk about the most secular calendar
I can think of which is the American consumer calendar.
Meaning it's structured around holidays.
that are built to sell things. Right? So we just had Memorial Day sell barbecue supplies and flags.
We're going to have now Juneteenth has been added to the list. I think that's also going to
end up being a lot of barbecuing for most people. Fourth of July, sell fireworks, sell flags,
you know, Mother's Day, Father's Day is in there, buy gifts for dad, get the tie cake from Carvelle.
Valentine's Day, St. Patrick's Day, sell a lot of beer and green stuff, right, etc.
Right?
So this is the most about as secular as you could get of a calendar.
Even though some of those days are still named after saints, it's pretty secular.
That calendar, right, if you follow it, it will shape the rhythm of your life.
Yeah.
Right?
Right? And that's what it's designed for.
Right that's what this is eyes for retail establishments want that to shape the rhythm of your life that seasonal section at your local Walmart
Where they have the stuff for whatever the next one of these holidays that aren't really holy days per se in most cases
Right they're counting on that cycle they want that to shape your life. Oh now I go and I buy and consume this now I go and buy and consume that
Right, they'll shape your life it'll form you
This to me
Right is one of the worst back lashes of
Particularly the Puritan movements that come out of the Protestant Reformation
Bear with me here Protestant friends really think about this, right?
They had such an antipathy for like Saint Stays
Right.
So those parent movements, right, well most of those parent movements.
wouldn't celebrate Christmas. The birth of Christ. And some of them won't even
celebrate Easter, right? Pazka. But definitely, we don't want a lot of, you know,
feast days. I think it's in the Westminster standards that says, you must guard
against the proliferation of Saint Stays. Nice. Protect everyone from this, right?
So
So all of this stuff from the Christian, the turtical calendar gets removed, right?
And most American Christianity, American evangelicalism really comes out of those pure and
movements just historically.
But then what do you end up centering even your church life around?
Right?
Yeah.
Mother's Day sermons.
You're gonna have a father's day service
You're going to have a liturgical calendar one way or another.
Yeah.
You know, for the July servants where you sing patriotic songs.
I know.
Get a church, right?
All of these things, right?
It's the same thing.
You've just chosen the most secular possible version.
What I want to know is, and I'm pretty sure the answer to this question is yes.
I just haven't encountered it yet because I haven't googled it up yet.
Are there Amazon Prime Day sermons?
Proud of the lives you're...
I know there are Black Friday sermons. Oh, absolutely. Yeah.
So
Right, just pause and think about it for a minute. What's better?
Right to base and structure your liturgical life on the life of Christ
Right at the stories about Christ recounted in the Bible or to base the cycles of your church life on
random
holidays that often don't even have any particular religious significance.
Yeah. Right. I mean the answer to that seems so obvious to me. Right. And I think the Puritans would
be horrified by the July service and other stay-in-fathers-day servants. Right. So think about that.
But this is why again the calendar is so important.
But so...
You end up, if you're on any calendar at all,
you end up with these cycles.
Right?
And the key thing here is about,
again, that cycle being connected to eternity.
That cycle coming around and bringing you back
to eternal realities over and over and over again.
Because we in this life on this earth
Cannot participate in those eternal
realities eternally yet. This is why St. Peter couldn't build the booths on Mount
Tabor at the Transfiguration. This is why Moses had to go down from the mountain.
We're not able as humans to live perpetually in these eternal realities.
That's what we're looking forward to. That's what we're hoping for.
in the age to come that we can live eternally in those realities.
But we can't hear in this world.
But what we can do is live our life in a series of cycles, concentric cycles, as it were,
that lead us out into the world and then back to those eternal realities again,
over and over and over again, and form our life around that.
that structure of return. Right? So as we mentioned, there's this frame story with Moses, right?
We're getting this from Moses's perspective on top of Mount Sinai. Moses is there with the angel
of the presence. Yeah. And the angel of the presence, if you go back to our Old Testament Christology
episodes.
This is one of the titles given in Second Temple Jewish literature for what we call the Second Yahweh figure, the Second Hypostasis of the God of Israel.
The Second Person, whatever language you want to use. Short version, this is Christ.
But one of the ways this is telegraphed in the text, right? He's referred to as the angel, the presence. Oh, well, it's an angel, right?
But every time he's describing
God's actions. He says we. Yeah. He says when God created the world, we did this. Yeah.
He's talking about what God did. It's not like when God created the world, we angels rejoiced.
No, it's it's it's this common action. Yes, it's when God created the world, we separated
light from darkness. Yeah right. So that's how this idea of
second person in the one God is conveyed. Again, this isn't full-blown
Trinitarian doctrine. But this is, again, the book of Jubilee is meditating
and commenting on things that we see in Genesis and Exodus, and presenting them
here in commentary for. And so there are all these places, again, you can go back
to that series we did.
where we see this second figure in Genesis and Exodus,
who he is now referring to.
Moses receives this as this vision.
Going into a little more detail then on the internal structure,
it's structured around, as we mentioned now, the Inocket Calendar.
And I mentioned a couple minutes ago this idea of sort of quote unquote consent.
So if you want to start with the smallest cycle, there's a weekly cycle.
Yeah, right with the Sabbath.
Yep.
And the Sabbath is on that one day, when it's observed on that one day a week,
is an entering into God's rest, which of us we've talked about.
It isn't God taking a break.
It's God being enthroned over his creation.
So it's an entering into the kingdom, the rule, the dominion of God, right?
Right, which is in it.
eternal thing, but that's entered into by humans on that one day.
And then they go back into the world and they do their work.
And then it comes around again. Right.
So there's this weekly cycle. Yeah.
And one thing I'll add to that is that if you read through the book,
and I encourage people to read it, like really this is one of the easiest ones to read,
you know, it's not going to lead you off into like wild, crazy speculative directions.
There's not the kind of symbolism and stuff that you get in some of the other,
Especially, yeah.
Yeah, but like one of the things you'll notice as you read it is the word week is used a lot and
You know it means generally when week is used in the text it just means any kind of seven
So like right sometimes. They'll say he fulfilled his week
Which means usually in that case seven years?
But but yeah, so we just mean seven but there are also Sabbath years
Yeah, exactly. Yeah. Yeah, yeah, so there's this the seven structure that's built into the text
Thanks for watching.
you see referenced over and over and over again.
Right. Every seventh year, people were to not go and work their fields and leave them
to the poor to go and work. Right. Now we know Israel never did that, but they were supposed
to. Right. So there was the weekly cycle of seven days. There was to be this yearly cycle
of seven years. There was also then every seven seven.
So after 49 years after seven Sabbath years there was to be a Jubilee year
When's book of Jubilee's comes from yeah and in that 50th year
Not only was it a Sabbath, but all debts were canceled all land was supposed to revert to the families
God had given it to in the Torah
Etc. Etc. Etc. Just like the Sabbath years were never actually practiced the Jubilee year was never actually practiced
We find out in the book of Jeremiah that's part of the reason for the exile
But that's how it was to be this is how the
These are the cycles that the the life of the people were to follow and then of course within each year
You have the cycle of feasts
Right the cycle of the feasts
At this point right there are some that come after the Torah, right?
So we don't have Purim we don't have Hanukkah, right?
But the ones in the Torah, you have on this yearly annual cycle.
Right? And each of those represents, again, a unique way of entering into particular eternal realities,
pertaining to and related to God.
Now, in communicating this, in communicating this,
As you read through the book of Jubilee's, you'll see what look like sort of crazy
anachronisms.
Yeah.
Right.
So you'll see like Noah celebrating Pentecost.
Yes.
And you're like Noah is celebrating the giving of the Torah at Mount Sinai.
Right.
What?
Yeah.
Or you'll see the...
the patriarchs, right, celebrating Passover and you're like, uh, Abraham? Wait. Yeah. Egypt. Yeah.
And that will seem odd for obvious reasons. But first of all, you gotta remember the text of the book
of Genesis. Yeah. Which Genesis itself does this. Right. So like Noah's getting on the ark, he has to
to go get all the-
the animals. He gets a certain number of the clean animals and a certain number of the
unclean animals. You're like, wait, where did we find out about clean and unclean animals?
That's in Leviticus, right? So Genesis itself does this. And why is it doing this? Right?
I mean, it seems non-sensical to us.
And part of that is because,
Even if you've been listening to this show for a long time, you may be thinking of, well,
so for example, the Passover or Pentecost is later people participating in the Exodus
from Egypt, or participating in the giving of the Torah at Sinai, people who lived maybe
hundreds thousands of years later. Right, participating in that same event.
But that's slightly off.
That's slightly off.
So those earthly events are places where
eternal realities sort of broke into the human experience of time.
And so the later people celebrating Passover
are not just participating in the earthly material event
of Israel leaving Egypt.
but they're participating in the eternal reality of God setting his people free from bondage,
ultimately to sin, to death, to the powers of evil. They're really entering into that
by way of entering into the place that that eternal reality broke into time.
Right. And that being the case, right, no, for example,
example, when Noah receives a covenant from God, he is in a sense participating in that
same eternal reality that will later break into human experience when the Torah is given
him outside of it.
Right?
Yeah.
So that's number one.
Well, just and just as not to belabor this point, but just to kind of connect it to one
we've made over and over again, just as when you know
Adam and Eve here, the feet of God in the Garden of Eden, they are participating in the incarnation,
which from a chronological point of view is not going to happen for thousands of years.
Right. He's not going to break into human experience for thousands of years.
Yeah, I'm just gonna
Throw out a big number
So we don't have, you know, tedious
emails. Billions and billions of
seconds of years.
Yeah.
So, uh,
yes, there's a conspiracy group now that says that the earth's only like,
I think it's like 2,500 years old.
Wow. Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, I've heard of this.
Yeah, the Targaryen people. Yeah.
So there you go, right?
Yuggers.
creationists, you wacky liberals, your old earth.
So, but that's sort of number one.
Number two, though, is, and this is important, too, in terms of how book of the book of
Jubilee sees this.
Remember, it sees what it's saying.
These are things being revealed to Moses.
Right.
So this is a view of
what the Torah is and what's going on in the Torah. We tend to, and this is partially a problem with
Torah being translated as law by way of nomos and lex that we've talked about before.
We won't belabor that again, but we think of it as well, this is God giving rules.
right? This is God giving commandments. And if we do
obey him, he gets upset. And does bad things to us. And if we obey him, that he's happy,
and he does nice things for us. And what that speaks to is a certain relationship between
the commandments and created reality that is wrong.
Yeah.
Right.
So I can make rules.
right that are just based on my own personal likes and dislikes that are you
know somewhat arbitrary right like you know if you're good if you're good at
drinking a drink in my house you have to put a coaster under it right now I have a
reason for that right I don't maybe I don't want you know rings left on my
furniture or maybe it's just because this is Louisiana and I don't want to
puddle
all over my floor from the condensation on your drink.
But whatever, for whatever reason I make that,
like if you don't do that, if you're over at my house and you don't put a coaster
onto your drink, and I don't see, like, nothing bad is going to happen to you.
That is just based on my own personal preferences.
And sometimes we think that God's commandments are that way too.
Yeah, right?
They're more like the laws of nature.
Right. Kind of laws.
Right. And so the way the book of Jubilee sees the Torah and the commandments of the Torah
and everything in the Torah is that these things are built into the creation.
Right. And so a prototype case of this is the first chapter and first couple verses
of the second chapter of Genesis. Right. Where the creation of the world, the creation
the heavens of the earth, the creation of the universe.
of everything is described in terms of a seven-day week, in terms of the Sabbath, in terms
of what humans are going to do of this cycle going forward. That that cycle of seven days,
the Sabbath is baked into. It is that structure for time is baked into the structure of the
universe, the structure of creation. And so when God gives the commandment about
resting on the seventh day. Right? It's not that, you know, every day is really the same,
but God is telling you to do this certain thing on this certain day. It's no, God is revealing
to you this part of the structure of the universe and time.
Yeah. And also for all those, there's a handful of people out there who probably do not listen
this show but nonetheless there are people
out there who say things like morality can be revised. This is why morality cannot be revised.
That's innocent period. Right. Because it's about the nature of another universe. Yeah. Yeah.
Maybe you think we're in a multiverse and you could go to another universe where something you
want to do is morally good that isn't here. But, right. Like you go live at the
the Terran Empire and murder is good.
But in our universe and everybody has been like Van Dyke's
Yes
This universe killing people is bad
Right always has been always will be
Yeah, so these things are and God is just revealing them and he's revealing them to humanity so that
Humanity as God's creation can flourish and live within God's creation. Yeah
by knowing about these.
things. Right. So again, this is revelation of what really is not commands given over a morally
neutral field. Right. Where, you know, like, or, you know, all your parents horrible rules when
you're a teenager that you decide you don't have to follow as soon as you leave hope. Right.
And then you turn 30 and it's like, wow, all of a sudden my parents are really smart and give good advice.
Right.
If they were giving good advice, it was good advice all along.
So yeah, so, so it's a question of these things being built into, into creation.
That's how Jubilee sees it.
And so you have most
of the content of the Torah, both in terms of feasts and in terms of particular,
quote unquote, regulations, particular commandments concerning all kinds of things,
just sort of inserted into the narrative of Genesis as you go through it in the book of Jubilee.
Right? Not in random places where they're inserted is relevant, but they're sort of back inserted
into genesis and you're like well this is from Exodus or this is from Leviticus or this
from numbers or this is from Deuteronomy, right? But the idea is that it's hardwired, it's built
into the world, right? And Moses has it revealed to them that, oh, here's where you can see it,
you can see that it's built into the world, right? So that said, we now move to the second part
of the second half. There we go. Or the second half of the second half. The lightning round.
tonight.
Yeah, this is the part where we talk about.
The board of order.
Yeah, this is the part where we talk about the many places that the book of Jubilee is
either, I think there are three categories.
There's traditions that Jubilee represents that are also referred to in the New Testament,
right, that aren't in the Old Testament.
There's possibly references to the book of Jubilee's directly, and then there's even
more directly quotes from
or things that are very close to being quotes from.
Language who lifted from, if not quotes,
like lifted from Jubilee.
Yeah, yeah.
So there's things that Jubilee's knows or says
or however you wanna put it,
that the New Testament repeats,
but that are not in the Old Testament.
And several of them are in the sermon
that St. Stephen gives as he's about to be stoned.
There are a cut scene please.
important to both you and me.
Yeah, there are a couple of places in the detestable where you find sort of little clusters
of references to these traditions, the Jubiles, which is part of what I think justifies
identifying them as traditions of Jubiles, right?
The fact that certain speakers and authors, right, make a bunch of references that seem
to refer to things of Jubiles, right?
in some cases.
in some relatively short texts.
And there are other places where you just find scattered references.
Yeah.
And some of, and a number of them are like, I don't know, I don't want to call them
on important details, but not super important details.
The things that are not really, you wouldn't base doctrine on or anything like that.
If they were there, you wouldn't notice.
Right.
And this is the kind of stuff that frankly, until I was looking at this list, you know,
when we were, when we were briefing the other day, I didn't really think too much about
like, oh, that's, wait, that's not in the Old Testament, you know, stuck like, where was Jacob
buried? Well, yeah, yeah, the details there. So to frame this, and I really want to frame this
with state-see-it-speed, because this is one of the, um, always like to take shots at uh,
the biblical scholarship. So you would be hard pressed today.
to find a lot of people outside of maybe conservative evangelical scholars. You would be hard-pressed to find a lot of people who think that the words, the words, not the concepts or so, but the actual words of St. Stephen's sermon in Acts 7
have any direct connection to the person of St. Stephen, the historical person.
Right. The best you would probably get is, well, you know, St. Lucas clearly in a lot
of cases summarizing, reconstructing. St. Luke wasn't there, so he's kind of reconstructing
a sermon from St. Stephen based on certain things, right? Maybe he talked to St. Paul,
who was there, right?
And St. Paul said, well, he talked about XYZ.
And St. Lucas.
reconstructed it. That's the best you'd get. The other end is just, oh, it's made up. Right.
It has no connection to anything. Right. Frankly, most scholars now don't think they like to contrast
St. Paul's sermons and acts with his epistles. The ones they accept are from him.
Amazing. Right. So, uh, but as we're going to see, we're going to talk about just right off the bat,
places, four places in St. Stephen's sermon in Acts 7 that reference traditions in the
Book of Jubilies. And we're not going to have any other quotes from the Book of Acts
in our list of references. Yes, just this one spot, right? Meaning St. Luke or whatever
you want to call the author.
If he's making this one up for St. Stephen, and inserting this, decided that St. Stephen would
quote, would reference the book of Jubilee's a bunch of times, and that St. Peter, St. Paul,
all the other St. Philip, all the other people whose speeches he recounts at the book of
of acts would not at all.
Right.
What is the more...
Let's just,
Occam's razor.
Right.
As to why this one would be different in that regard than all the other ones.
Yeah.
That maybe St. Stephen was thinking about the book of Jubilee's Allure knew it very well.
Or, you know, so it comes up.
Who was a student of Gamelio?
Well, see, St. Paul, it is, it is sermons and acts, doesn't reference the book of Jubilee's
but doesn't his epistles.
Right, so it seems to be
The most obvious explanation for this kind of thing that you find when you look at the text closely is
this bears some connection to the historical St Stephen and
What he actually said that makes it different?
Yeah, because different preachers have different emphases that the other things being recounted. Yeah
So that said yes, so one of these is
in
verses 15 and 16, where he references the burial of
Jacob and Joseph in the patriarchs at Shackham, which is not actually recorded in Genesis
or the Torah later, but is mentioned in Jubilee's 46 verse 9.
Yeah, and that's you might think, okay, well, how why is that an important detail? Well,
it's not super important, like there's no doctrine to base on this, right? But remember,
they're all in Egypt at that point. So the idea that they would get all get
taken back to be buried in some other place is an extraordinary action. They didn't just stick
them wherever they, the nearby cemetery or whatever. And St. Stephen's sermon in Acts 7, he's running
through sort of the early history of Israel, right? So he's sort of running through the material
that the book of Jubilee's runs through. Right? And so what we see is that as he runs through those
stories and
runs through that material, he just throws in these details that are also in the book of Jubilee's.
Right? And doesn't he doesn't pause and say, well, now wait guys, okay, this is just a tradition.
This isn't actually in the Bible, but right.
He references Moses being 40 years old when he killed the Egyptian.
And act 723 which is in Jubilee's 47 10 through 12.
He references Moses having spent 40 years in Midian and Acts 730 which is in Jubilee's 48 verse 1.
And then probably the the biggest one. And I say the biggest one because this not only is mentioned by
St. Stephen, but this shows up two other places in the New Testament. Yeah. Yeah. Is St. Stephen's
reference in Acts 7 verse 53 to the law having been given by angels? Yeah. I mean it's explicit there.
It's explicit in Jubilee's.
There is, I think that there were some reference to God coming in Sinai with all of his holy ones or something like that, but it's
it's not quite the same thing.
Yeah, Deuteronomy 32 and that's sort of.
Yeah.
So that's a notoriously hard to translate passage, but anyway, yeah.
Right. It's not explicit that the law was given through angels in the Old Testament, although it is explicit in the New Testament,
and it's explicit in the book of Jubilee is from this one big detail.
that gets that's wrong and the Cecil B. Demell movie.
There's not only to say Stephen mentioned it in Acts 7, verse 53, St. Paul mentions this
in Galatians 3, verse 19 and it's mentioned in Hebrews 2, verse 2.
Yep. Yep.
So this is repeated and a Jewish friend of mine, when he looked at St. Paul saying it got
really mad about this. Believe it or not.
and said, oh see, this is the New Testament trying to marginalize the Torah.
What?
By saying it was just given by angels and not by God.
And finally, I had to say, dude, that's just the Book of Jubilee's man.
The book of Jubilee's.
And he was kind of like, oh, okay.
So, but I mean, it's not just that that's not a detail mentioned in the Torah, right?
In
in the Old Testament, it's that, right, that there are people who would even, you know,
be offended by that idea, right, because they don't know where that tradition is from.
Right.
That's a tradition that's foreign to the Old Testament, but that is recorded in Jubilee's,
at least.
Again, we can't say that comes from Jubilee's, because Jubilee's probably received it from
somewhere.
Yeah.
Another little sort of mini nexus of references is in
second Peter, which is a pretty short text, right? But we find three, well, two references
in a quote, frankly, in second Peter. So second Peter, second Peter, two verse five,
refers to Noah, the preacher of righteousness, which again, read Genesis, everybody, to whom
does no a preach in Genesis. Nobody. Yeah, it's not it's not.
there but there he was righteous but there's nothing about him preaching yeah yeah but
if he says yeah they Peter says he was a preacher of righteousness right preacher of righteousness
if you go to Jubilee 7 verses 23 39 you not only hear about Noah preaching but it's got one of
his sermons there you go like printed there that he preached two people right and then when
Second Peter 313 talks about the restoration of creation.
right the restoration of the created world. He uses language.
Even if you don't want to say this is a quote, he uses language that's pretty clearly drawn from
at least the same well. He's very reminiscent.
That's, yeah, that if it's not quoted, if it's not a direct reference,
it's definitely drawn from the same well as the Book of Jubiles.
So like in second Peter 313 he says
But according to his promise we are waiting for new heavens and a new earth in which righteousness dwells.
Okay, that's be very familiar to everybody. So here's the passage from Jubilee's chapter 1 verse 29.
This is not the whole verse, but from the day of creation until the day of the new creation,
when the heaven and earth and all of their creatures shall be renewed,
according to the powers of heaven and according to the whole nature of earth,
until the sanctuary of the Lord is created in Jerusalem upon Mount Zion.
So probably...
not a quote, but definitely kind of a very similar thought. Although St. Peter says in
a much brief, brief, brief, brief, brief, brief, brief, pulling language of the new heavens
and the new earth, right? Yeah. And the dwelling of God. And then, uh, second Peter 3,
eight folks may be familiar with St. Peter pointing out that one day is like a thousand years.
He's not the first person to say that.
That's in Jubilee's 4, verse 30.
And...
Jubilies may also not be the first person to say that, but that's the first place where
we find it in Jewish literature.
And again, when we see a little nexus like this in Second Peter, of multiple things seems
to make a pretty good case that the author was familiar with the book of Jubilies and
was kind of drawing on that language.
Yeah.
Any one of them, you might say, well, it's kind of a coincidence, but like multiple close
similarities like that.
a very short letter.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
So there are a couple of places where Christ seems to, I would say essentially quote, but
at least draw on the language of or use the language of.
This first one especially to me, I think is a quote.
I would argue is a quote.
Yeah, so in Luke chapter 1149, the Lord says,
therefore also the
wisdom of God said, which that's him. Therefore also the wisdom of God said, I will send them
prophets and apostles, some of whom they will kill and persecute. Again, very familiar
for those who know the New Testament. And then Jubilee's verse 1, chapter 1, verse 12.
So this is, this is right at the beginning of the book. And I shall send to them witnesses
so that I might witness to them, but they will not hear. And they will even kill the witnesses,
and they will persecute those who search out the law. And they will neglect everything
in the beginning.
evil on my side. So again, a longer, longer in Jubilee's almost
well, yeah, when I say that's a quote, you have to remember a bunch of things,
right? Right? Like St. Luke's Gospel is written in Greek. Right. And the translation of
Jubilee's we just read is from Gehaz. Right. And these are both into English. Right.
Right. It's also important to note though that right. Christ says that in Luke 11
49 quoting the wisdom of God, right?
the wisdom of God said this, right? In Jubilee's it's the angel of the presence who says that. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. So another one, this is from John 14 verse 26, but the helper, the Holy Spirit,
whom the Father will send in my name, he will teach you all things and bring to your remembrance all
that I have said to you. Again, very familiar. And then Jubilee's chapter 32 verses 25
and then 26A, like the first half of 26. But you write down everything just as you have seen
and read it. And Jacob said, Oh Lord, how will I remember everything that I've read and saw
and he said to him, I will cause you to remember everything. So this is a very similar thought
with a lot of the same words. You know, this is after Jacob's vision
and that Bethel of the latter to heaven.
Yeah, or the same as we've talked about so this is this encounter
between him and God
That kind of an artificial mountain, right? Yeah at the mountain, right?
Yeah, and then
St. Paul
interestingly
in 2 Corinthians 6
He's got he gives as St. Paul is want to do he'll give sort of a whole pile of scripture quotes
votes.
several different places all in a row, right?
Sort of a katana of quotations from different places.
And at the end of his group of scripture quotes,
there's a quote that really seems to be coming from
the book of Jubilays.
Yeah.
So second Corinthians 6, 18, he says,
and I will be a father to you and you should be
and daughters to me says the Lord Almighty. In Jubilee's chapter 1 verse 24,
and their souls will cleave to me into all my commandments and they will do my commandments,
and I shall be a father to them and they will be sons to me. So again, very similar language.
Right. And if you look in your English Bible, because your English Bible
realizes that this is a
list of scripture quotes, right? So they'll have the references for the series of quotes.
When they get to verse 18, they will reference that to second Samuel, I think second
Samuel 7 to the covenant with David. Where God says to David, I will be a father to you
and you will be a son to me in the singular. Just as sons, not sons and daughters, says,
I'll be a father you will be a son to me talking about him being the king.
Right, the king is the son of God, right?
Because they're trying that they could tell St. Paul is quoting something here.
Everything else is scripture.
So they try to find something close, right?
But in
Jubilee's it's in the plural and
Like the way St. Paul uses it, it's talking about everyone who keeps the commandments of God.
Yeah, not talking about
king and it's in the plural. So it's rather closer to Jubilee's than so. Yes, it seems more like he's
quoting Jubilee's just from certain points of view regarding the Bible, that would be highly
problematic. I'm to quote that in a list of scripture quotations. Not from mine, mind you, but
for a lot of people.
Here's why it wouldn't be problematic.
cards on the table. Here's why I don't think it's problematic. I don't think that is any more problematic for St. Paul
then
St. Stephen
narrating through Genesis and adding these other things that aren't in Genesis.
He doesn't feel the need to stop and say okay wait this bit isn't in the Bible.
Right. Right. Right. Because he has received the scriptures within a greater body of tradition.
The scriptures have been handed down to him, so has a means of interpreting and applying and understanding them.
And that's all of a piece.
It's the same thing, true for St. Paul.
So he does a few to distinguish between
what comes out of the text of Scripture and what is
a traditional interpretation of it.
So then there's a bunch of places where St. Paul just draws on language
that we also find in the book of Jubilee's.
So in 2 Thessalonians 2 and verse 3,
this is where he's talking about the man of lawlessness,
all of thisness, right?
coming Antichrist, we talked about this in our Antichrist episode. But one of the titles he uses
to refer to the Man of Lawlessness, besides Man of Lawlessness, is the Son of Tradition.
And in Jubilee's 10 verse 3, the Son's of Tradition, that's a title that's given to the Giants.
Well, by the way, there's Giants, everybody. There's Giants. Yeah, by the way.
Yeah, we'll get more on more on that later. Yeah
There are giants in the book of Jubilee.
It's getting excited.
So in Galatians 2 verse 15,
St. Paul makes the comment,
we are not Gentile sinners, right?
That phrase, which seems kind of odd from St. Paul,
and that we don't find elsewhere in the New Testament,
but you do find that in Jubilee's 23 verses 23 and 24.
Yeah.
One of the most telling ones, this was one that gives people fits and is spawned so many
lousy journal, I mean so many journal articles. A lot of them in jets, a lot of them in the
journal of the evangelical theological society is that in Galatians 3, verse 17, St. Paul says
that there were 430 years from Abraham to Moses. Why is that a problem you might say?
Well, you go and add up the years in Genesis and Exodus.
It's not 430 years from Abraham to Moses.
In fact, if you go by Genesis and Exodus,
the Israelites spent 430 years in Egypt.
Abraham, of course, was, you know, century before that.
Yeah, so
You know
That was gonna say oh St Paul made an oopsie
Well actually that's not true most old testament scholars say St Paul made an oopsie
Most local scars just say oh St Paul got that wrong. That's an error in the Bible
But obviously for certain people as I mentioned the evangelical theological society certain folks
Their approach to the Bible won't let that sit so they have to find a way
to make that work. Up to and including, I've even read articles about this where they say,
St. Paul was right. Genesis and Exodus are wrong. Wow. Amazing. The text of Genesis and Exodus
got corrupted somehow and St. Paul is correcting it. Yeah, but it turns out.
The inspiration of the Holy Spirit. Yeah, it turns out that this number matches
passage in Jubilee is Jubilee is 15-4.
Now this might be something where he's literally referencing Jubilee's, he got it from Jubilee's,
but it may also be simply that as we said, Jubilee's represents when it quotes the scriptures,
it seems to represent a separate Hebrew manuscript tradition than any other we know about.
Yeah, that could be too.
So it could be that.
It could be that.
Yeah, yeah.
But Galatians 3, 17 seems to directly contradict Exodus 1240, right?
matches Jubilee's 15.
for. Yeah. Right. I first of all, all this dating stuff just makes my eyes roll back in my head.
Indeed.
Boring. But also, right, we've talked before the show a bunch of times about numbers and numbers
being preserved in texts and languages that don't have numerals. Right. St. Paul is referencing a
tradition about the amount of time.
Right.
And there were probably as Father Andrew alluded to.
There were probably Hebrew texts and Greek texts with all different numbers.
Yeah.
I mean, we know this independently of all this.
Like if you compare the old Greek to the Hebrew texts that we have, various numbers don't
match to the place.
No, but they're all over the place.
Yeah.
They don't match.
So, and then there's a couple of places where there's language used.
Uh
in the book of Revelation that matches very closely with language used in
Jubilee. One of those is in Revelation 1 verse 6 and Revelation 5 verse 10, God
talks about making the church a kingdom and priests, which is uncommon, right?
what you find in the Old Testament is a kingdom of priests.
And that when it makes its way into Greek is often read as a royal priesthood.
You can see how kingdom of priests, royal priesthood.
Right.
Same idea.
But that's of not and.
Right.
Whereas Jubilee 1618 uses the and conjunction.
and then in Revelation 4, 5, 11, 19, and 16, 18.
I'm Jack Van Impeying it up again. It refers to the angels of the voices and of the thunder and of the lightnings
and these angels are referenced in Jubilee's two verse two.
And not directly referenced in any of the canonical scriptures.
So, yeah, Revelation in general.
to see this someday when we talk about the book of Enic. Is there a
repository for a lot of Second Temple Jewish apocalyptic literature themes and
that kind of thing, even from outside the Old Testament scriptures? And then
just a couple of notes to finish out this half of this half of the show. A couple
of liturgical things.
There's a prayer that Noah says in Jubilee's after the flood.
Yeah, which will read the whole thing a little bit later.
Later on, yeah, we're going to come back to this.
But that's a prayer about protection from demonic spirits for himself and his descendants.
And it begins with O God of Spirits and of all flesh, which if you've...
bent to a memorial service in an Orthodox Church, you may notice the central
prayer of our memorial for the departed begins the same way. And we also have in
Jubilee 16 verse 30 our earliest known reference to crowning to the couple being
crowned in terms of a wedding service.
Pretty good.
As a traditional practice at weddings.
Nice.
All right, while the lightning round is over,
so we're going to go ahead and wrap up the second half
and we'll be right back with the third and final half
of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
You've probably heard of St. Rafael Halloweeny, St. Alexander Hodovitsky, liturgical translator
Isabel Habgood, and other righteous men and women who made their mark on the early
development of Orthodoxy in America.
But what about the notorious, itinerant Bulgarian monk, or Father Rafael Morgan, the first
Black Orthodox priest in America, or Vera Johnston, who served the Orthodox Church without renouncing
her Theosophist roots?
their stories.
many others, some edifying, some appalling, all entertaining, make up the lost histories
of the early decades of Orthodox Christianity in the continental United States. Lost
histories, the good, the bad, and the strange in early American Orthodoxy by Matthew
name. Out now at store.enginefaith.com. Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hey, welcome back.
It's a good book, by the way, that was just advertised.
And I have a grievance.
Oh.
With Nami's, Nami's books.
the subtitle.
Oh, right. He references the good, the bad and the ugly there. Yes. I'm going to bet
Leavand cleave is not even in that book. Charles Bronson, maybe you'll Brenner, maybe
no, Leavand cleave. You'll Brenner was the north of oxygen Christian, by the way.
You probably was Charles Bronson. Oh, that's right. He was a Ukrainian, is he? That's why
they might be in the book. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I just.
just add a little extra on my YouTube channel.
You can actually see me interview Matthew about the book,
and he tells some of the,
here comes the shameless self-promotion.
That are in it.
Yeah, exactly.
Hey, I'm the Stan Lee of,
I'd like you to subscribe, everybody,
and hit that bell.
It's true.
You get notifications when he drops a new video.
It's a new video.
All right.
Well, we're talking about the book of Jubilee's,
and now we're going to talk about,
in more detail, some of the contents
Okay.
you know, directly, not just quotes that are found in other things or references
or whatever, but actually some of the direct contents of what you can find in
the book of Jubilee. So this is sort of a preview. And again, I recommend
everybody read it. Surprise. Nobody is called in about all these shocking
revelations. I know. I know. Well, there's an argue with me about something.
They're all just listening in wrapped attention. So, yeah. No, they're all
gonna go talk smack on social media because they know I'm not there.
Oh
Coward
Colin and fight me. He does read it all. He's wandering around looking for someone to debate.
Yes. So, okay, so it's a vision given to Moses begins with the creation. Big shock.
Yes, because it's going through Genesis. Yeah. Yeah, so what we're going to go through in this
third half and unlike the third half of Thomas Aquinas' summa.
This is actually going to be us. It would have been a funny joke that three people would have gotten.
If like you and I had left for the third half and someone had just tried to do the third half on their own from our notes.
Anyway.
A little too subtle for most people I think.
Yes. Too subtle for the Western mind.
So we're going to be really going through in this third half.
We're obviously not going to be able to because we come out people you've heard whole council of God like if I tried to go through the book of Jubilee's in detail
We'd be here for weeks, right? Yeah, this is some highlights not even all the possible highlights things that are interesting to me
Supplemented by things that are interesting to Father Andrew that's exactly here from the book of Jubilee's
so
Within the creation account right within that story
in the story of Paradise of the Garden of Eden,
just some interesting details, interesting to me.
As we've talked about before,
Jubilee's like everything else.
Oh, by the way, everything else except Milton.
I should say we've gotten a reaction on YouTube
about the fact that no one's called.
One person says, actually I think this is from Priest.
He says, I'm too shocked to react.
So there's
That's possible.
There it is.
People are just an abject horror.
That's right.
So like everything else except Milton, the Book of Jubilee's does not have angels being created
and or falling before the creation of the world.
It Jubilee's, they are created on the first day.
And as you talked about before, the first day and the fourth day are the most...
common in second-term literature and the church fathers. Sometimes you also get the second day
interestingly, but usually the first day or the fourth day. Yeah. First day is obvious because
it's the formation of light and the stars and this kind of stuff. Well light. Yeah, light,
light, sorry. Yeah, and for the fourth day is the stars. So that's good, you know, those days are connected.
everything. There are some interesting news when when woman is created she wasn't
named Eve yet. Immediately after the story of her creation from Genesis it gives
the commandments regarding a woman's purification after childbirth.
Yeah. So this is one of those inserts we were talking about. Yeah which there's
There's no babies yet.
Right, right. We're nowhere near Kane being born. Right. We're nowhere near her getting pregnant, let alone giving birth.
But this is broad in these commandments are broad in input here. So as I mentioned, this is a good test case. I mentioned it's not accidental where the author puts these things. This is part of how he communicates.
And what he's doing this to communicate is in part his interpretation, which we've also given before on this show,
of what's going on with the creation.
woman specifically with what it means when God says it is not good for man to be alone.
Right. Our very modern psychological individualist interpretation of this is,
oh Adam was lonely. He didn't have anyone to talk to. Right. He named all the animals, but
animals can't talk. Right. Well, we're going to find out that's not true either. But, uh,
Right, but even thinking about just in the biblical text all by itself.
Right? He was with God. Yeah. Right? God is there. The angels that why would he be lonely? Yeah. Right?
This is not a psychological thing. I'll say, are you going to say God wasn't enough for him? I mean, come on. Right.
He's it's not good that he's alone is referring to the fact that all of the plants and animals that God created were reproducing after their
kind. Yeah. The zebras were making more zebras. The elephants were making more elephants.
The oak trees were making more oak trees. Adam couldn't make more atoms is. Right. You
couldn't make more humans. This is why women is created. So that together they can make
more humans. Right. And so talking about childbirth right after that is a way of conveying
That
that emphasis and that interpretation.
There's another interesting detail that's given in that same context,
and that's that Adam, according to Jubiles,
was in the land where he was created for 40 days before he was brought to Eden.
Yeah, which I mean, in Genesis it does say that God created them
and then put him in the garden.
So there's this chronological order works,
works, but you got to get this other detail of he was 40
days outside of Eden, and then he's brought in.
And what's that about? Well, we talked about, back on the Lent episode, most recently,
that 40 days represents a period of purification and preparation. Right? So he was being purified
and prepared after his creation to enter into Eden, to enter into the presence of God.
Yep
Right, and this has deliberate like priestly overtones
Yeah
Right.
And, and, right, is related to the idea of Eden as Temple.
And it also gives chronologically, says that
man and woman were in paradise for seven years
before the explosion for paradise.
of perfection in it.
It's one Sabbath of years, one Sabbath year.
These cycles.
So that's the first seven years there in Paradise.
When it's going through the expulsion for Paradise
and the curses, they're placed on them.
It says, regarding the serpent, and only the serpent,
God says that he will be angry.
with him forever.
No worry.
His wrath will be on him forever.
Yeah.
Not man or woman.
Right.
Immediately after he's expelled from paradise, Adam offers a sacrifice, and the sacrifice he
offers is a morning incense offering.
There you go, celebrating orthros.
It lists the type of incense that he burns, right?
And of course, this is again the first commandment in Exodus about the worship of God is the offering of incense at morning and evening, right?
So this is pushed backward.
Adam starts this as soon as he's out of paradise, right?
This cycle of worship starts the stale cycle of worship.
It's also mentioned there that, whether it's well for paradise, all the animals lose their ability to...
talk before that apparently they could all talk. Yeah they ruined Narnia. And it's
interesting. Adam offering incense. I mean that's a very sort of priestly
priestly thing to do. You know, right. Yeah, he's the man. That's his job. He's right
exactly. So yeah. And so the whole thing with animals not talking. This isn't
supposed to be a Disney thing or whatever.
Dr. Too little has lost.
as powers. It's that's a way of representing the fact that after the expulsion from paradise,
man is sort of alienated from the rest of the creation. So that being able to like
converse with a cow, right, is like an image of, right, man is connected, right, to the rest
of creation there's this cooperation, right? Whereas after the expulsion now animals become...
dangerous to humanity. There's this separation and alienation and breaking of
relationship with creation. At the time of the creation of the angels on the first
day, the angels get assignments. Yeah, which angels get assigned to all kinds of
stuff right which which there's
In the Bible, there are references to this.
It's just assumed.
And often you get it in lists in the Psalms, where
David or whoever's writing the Psalm is talking to the angels,
and then by the way, it starts mentioning elements
of creation that in the same list, as though they're all one group.
And you get stuff like that.
But in Jubilee's, it's made explicit.
So when you're
created God makes them and then sets them over different things. So I'm going to read that
passage because I think it's just really interesting. And this connects us back. We mentioned earlier
those references in the book of Revelation, angels of the voices and the thunder of the lightenings,
right? So this is where that comes from. This is Jubilee's 2-2. For on the first day he created the
heavens which are above and the earth and the waters and all of the spirits which minister before him.
angels of the presence and the angels of sanctification and the angels of the spirit of fire and the angels of the spirit of the winds and
the angels of the spirit of the clouds and darkness and snow and hail and frost and the angels of
resoundings and thunder and lightning. There's that thing that's referenced in Revelation and the angels of the spirits of cold and heat and
and winter and springtime and harvest and summer,
and of all the spirits of his creatures,
where
are in heaven and on earth. So it's notable among other things that there are angels in charge of
each of the four seasons. And as I have said, occasional public speaking engagements, if I ever get
to know are the angels of are the angels in charge of the hotel or of that landscaping service.
Yes.
some of both. Who is the patron angel of Link?
and then we'll see what this
call has to say. But yes, so
there's, you know, I would, if
I were to get a chance to speak
to the angel of autumn, I would
say, look number one, I love your
work. You're the, don't tell the
other ones, but you're the best
seasonal angel. And number two, the
question I have is, you know, pumpkin
spice lattes. Is that your idea
of the angel of autumn? I would say
look number one, I love your work.
Pumpkin Spice Laties. Is that your...
idea or is it some kind of twisting, you know, of the original deposit of goodness of autumn.
So yeah, let's find out what our callers is about.
Well, I can answer that second question.
Okay.
And yes, I think pumpkin spice is the evidence that that angel is fallen.
Like, when we get to the book of Enek, we'll find out like each of the watchers communicated
this secret terrible knowledge to the women they seduced?
And somewhere there is a white woman who was seduced and given the terrible secret of pumpkin spice.
Wow! See this may be the thing that finally gets you canceled, Father Steve.
Alright, well we do have a caller. So we have Gregory calling from Florida, I believe.
So Gregory, welcome to Lord Spears Podcast.
And thank you for bringing me on.
Yeah, yeah, so you'll Florida, man.
Yes, all know I'm my trans
I'm in the military so I got put here.
Oh, oh, oh.
Well, so in regard to the angel of autumn,
I would have to say, firstly, that why did they have favorites?
Because he definitely doesn't visit here.
And secondly, the whole pumpkin spice thing,
that's got to be that ancient wisdom from before the flood
that people are trying to rediscover through technology.
Because you can't make that without a machine, you know?
So you are.
See?
On my side.
I'm not taking a side here.
I've just asked you to control the pump.
spice controls the white women. That's all it is. Wow. Yeah, it has a point. Okay, so Gregory,
what does your question come to? Time and the experience of time of ours being kind of based on
ourselves, you know, we base our our experience on ourselves. And I'm wondering so far, I've got
me understanding that God is outside of that. But I'm still really kind of shaking on the shore
about like
and that are parted and angels and demons specifically.
And like, let's say other worshiping groups
is kind of broadening it maybe too much,
but you look like people like the new whole Norse-Pate movement, right?
Like, when they participate in rituals that sort of reenact times
that are law-onsense-past,
is it just not working?
Is it, are they doing something similar?
Is this a valid question?
All questions are valid or validly asked anyway.
Yeah, I mean, well, ritual works, right?
It's, I mean, some, of course, are kind of lame and made up, right?
But if they're done in seriousness, and especially if there is, especially if there's
some kind of spirit that wants to be involved, there is a thing happening.
You know.
So if a Norse neopagin wants to sacrifice to Thor and then eat that food, there's no reason
that Demon won't show up and want to be part of that because Demon's desire is to drag
us down into their darkness.
And the worshipper may understand himself as participating in something related to Norse
paganism.
But the point is not, is he like participating in Ragnarok, you know, although I hate to
imagine what that sacrifice would look like.
But, you know, that's not the point.
The point is, you know, what does it mean to participate in these realities?
Right?
So for a Christian to participate in the Eucharist, we receive the benefits of Christ's
death and resurrection.
Right?
That's what it means to participate in the Eucharist.
You know, um.
For a pagan to participate in demonic stuff, it's about communion with those demons.
Whatever the narrative packaging that goes in, that's put in.
So that is the reality.
And certainly spiritual beings function in a trans-temporal way.
They don't experience time and space the way that we do.
We don't know exactly.
like because we don't even notice like to be
a flying mammal. So much less a demon, you know, or an angel. So that's what I
think about that. I don't know. Father Stephen, what do you have to say to not
Florida man? Yeah. So I mean, yeah, in keeping with what Father Andrew said, we
have to keep in mind that most modern pagans are trying to participate in
these spiritual realities and like the most soy way possible.
I mean that's somewhat literally because a lot of the Mervegans, you know, like they're
not going to sacrifice a horse and drink its blood.
Okay?
You want to be a dors-pegid?
That's step one.
Okay?
If you can't do that, you can't kill a horse.
You're right out.
Sorry, ladies.
Um, yeah.
That's not pumpkin splice horse blood.
It's just straight up horse blood.
I mean, we have to distinguish that.
Kind of.
of larping from like those black metal musicians in Scandinavia who are like burning down
churches and killing each other and just painting it actual ritual sacrifice of things, right?
That's not to say that the larping and stuff is harmless, right?
Father Andrew said, you know.
even the kind of dumbest and lamest things like that.
There's some demon willing to try to take advantage of that, right?
Even though it's not as clearly demonic as some of those other examples.
But yeah, it's,
yeah, at most, right,
they're kind of building a community with those demonic spirits and
demonic spirits are shaping them.
the more intensely, I mean, just like we would say with Christianity, right? The more intensely
you actually follow the Christian way of life, the more you're going to be transformed
by it, right? The same thing is true on the other side, right? There's a bunch of people
who identifies as a pagan and someone who's deeply participating in actual pagan rights.
And you can see that in the behavior of people, right? In the way in which they are transformed
by those things.
But the things that they're participating in,
they're participating in these spirits, these demonic spirits, and
their qualities or attributes are shaping them.
But obviously, those demonic spirits are alienated from eternal realities.
That's why they can't grant any kind of eternal life.
because they don't really have it.
They're disconnected because the only truly
eternal reality is God.
Right?
And they're alienated from Him.
And so that's why going down that road
just brings destruction.
You don't become an eternal evil.
You just find destruction.
There's not sort of equal parity.
And in terms of the experience of time.
I mean, we'll do more episodes on this in the future.
We need to do one where we talk about the way our experience of time is related to memory.
Because that is deeply our memories.
So there have been studies recently, for example, we tend to think,
and I have even tended to think of the past, that time seems to go faster and faster as you get older.
You're probably not as old as
me, but maybe you've already experienced that a little bit. And I always kind of thought
that was because, well, when you're five years old, like one year is 20% of your life.
And when you're 50 years old, one year is 2% of your life. And so it just seems quicker,
right? That was my thought. But studies have actually shown that St. Augustine was right
in books 10 and 11 of the Confessions.
And our whole conception of time is experienced.
which I was deeply tied to our memory,
and that the reason time seems to go so much more slowly
when we're young is that we're constantly
having new experiences.
And the fact that we're constantly having new experiences
means we're constantly forming new memories.
Whereas by the time you're an old man like me,
your life has kind of fallen into this consistent cycle
of the same things over and over again every day, right?
And so you're not for
these new memories at the same rate because the experiences are not as new.
Right, and so the things kind of blur together and that causes time to seem to move
more quickly. And then if you actually deliberately go out of your way, this is
part of the studies. Like if you just said, I'm going to take a two-week vacation
every day I'm going to do something I've never done before or go somewhere I've
never gone before. That two weeks would seem really long to you.
Hmm
even looking back on it later because of all the new memories that you've
found. But so anyway, at some point in the future, we'll do an episode about our
experience of time where we talk about that link with memory.
Maybe explore what St. Augustine says about it.
I was going to say St. Augustine, I appreciate your way of working that out, is actually still
in philosophy is still basically what everybody uses. How about that?
That's exciting. I'm being again the news.
Parents notion. I've kind of been touching into that with my newborn son, but I've not.
I really formulated that notion all the way yet.
And as far as the whole North Pagan thing goes, I generally don't often run into them,
but in the military, you do see a fair enough amount because they all want to beards,
and they don't less outbeards unless you're a North Pagan.
But I guess the.
I was saying I swear it was the.
the idea of sacrificing a horse versus the pumpkin spice latte and
it blood is like sort of like us calling like something of pleasing a
Roma before the Lord and the Old Testament versus like strange incense for the
Lord like to them to the demons it's like a pumpkin spice latte really my
flavor I prefer you know human blood or something like that. Well yeah yeah it's
a question of you know how far and how fast you're going down the same road
right it's the same road but there are people who are kind of
and dabbling and tiptoeing and there are people.
who are just running in that direction.
Yeah, I don't know.
Thank you so much.
All right, take my call.
Yeah, thanks for calling, Gregory.
So we actually do, now suddenly we're getting people calling.
So I guess people are inspired here.
Are they angry white women based on my comments?
I don't know, I don't know.
They're calling from a Starbucks inside a target.
We'll find out, but our next caller is Maureen.
So Maureen, welcome to the Laura Spears podcast.
Are you here to ream Father Stephen out?
I'm going to ask you to
ask me a question.
Marina, are you there?
Speak to us, Marina.
Who did this to you?
Yeah, because I was.
Oh, there we go.
Oh, you can hear me now.
Oh, good.
Yes.
Welcome.
I, um, I missed a little bit of the last few minutes
because I was in the process of making the connection here.
my phone and listening through my phone.
to. Why were you talking about the pattern of the different
Judaism that I heard this before but it's suddenly dawned on me that the
the many friends or rivers or whatever in the society then
We sort of have the same pattern today in our modern society in a number of different ways.
And I thought about my, I thought about my, my cultural enlightenment,
paradigm of looking at the world and
pseudoscientific, there must be a right answer.
And it dawn on me and this may need correction,
is there maybe not a right answer
because we're talking about things above our pay grade,
I guess you'd say.
And maybe it's see a Wogema or whatever you call it,
or something along the Western mystic,
like Julian of Norwich or St. John of the Cross,
where it inspires us to listen.
star heart to God and be open to new insight without being sure that it's absolutely correct
or whatever or I'm sorry this is very foggy but my thoughts are foggy, I'm trying to sort
them out.
Okay.
So, one of the things that you said that I,
hopefully I understand this correctly.
You
You talked about patterns of behavior that are in the ancient world that seem to be repeating even now
Right that that human society
Still kind of works in a lot of the same ways
And I mean I definitely think that that's true certainly there's big differences
There's a huge difference for instance between the ancient world dominated by paganism and the modern world
deeply influenced by Christianity everywhere
Yeah.
But nonetheless, people are still people, we're still sinners, we still commit the same kinds of sins, basically.
And so, even though they get expressed in different ways within different cultures, I mean, definitely, humans are humans.
Right? And also, above us, or beneath us, or beside us, whatever, you also have spiritual beings who are influencing us.
Right? And they're still around. It's the same, you know, the same bunch.
So, let's get started.
in fluing, so I'm in one way or another.
So yeah, there definitely are patterns that one can see
kind of repeating throughout history,
individually in humans and then in humans as groups as well.
I mean, that's the bit that I would respond to
of what you said.
Does that, is that helpful at all?
Well, it is in a way, it's helping me articulate
what I'm trying to say, but I've got the training
the training in the Enlightenment Parade.
that says there must be a right answer and follow the science and all that stuff, which
is actually science is a not real science. But in order to grasp all the wonderful, I
love this stuff. It's really cool. I do wonder if we aren't looking for answers, we're
just looking for.
spiritual insights that might mean something to us without necessarily having the full fact because
We're mere human beings and we can't know that
Yeah, so yeah, let me go ahead father. Yeah, go ahead. Yeah, so yeah, I think I get we get we have a tendency as modern people
To
Want to know things in kind of an external way
We've talked before the show that there are multiple ways of knowing.
And modernity kind of only has one.
It wants to turn everything into a science.
Mathematics-based science is the only way to really know things.
And people even approach religion that way.
Sometimes people who inquire into the Orthodox church who I talk to approach things in that way.
They're sort of like, well, I'm interested in the Orthodox church,
I don't know what-
topics XYZ ABC right and they sort of want me to kind of argue them into
believing what the Orthodox Church teaches is the right answer about XYZ ABC
right and then if I give arguments and and explanations that satisfy them then
they'll say oh okay I'll join the church right and then I'll tell them to wait a
here and they won't get what.
Right. Um, we're like, no, I'm ready. I decided. Right. Um, and you can't really know very much,
at least very much that's worth anything. That way in that external way. Uh, because you don't
get any wisdom that way. You can't explain this to anyone under 25. Sorry guys. I know some of
of your very mature but when I was under
I thought I knew everything from reading books, right?
And therefore I knew everything.
And I was smarter than other people.
I knew things they didn't know.
And I realized at a certain point that pretty much everyone older than me actually knew more than I did, but they knew it in a way that I didn't have access to because I hadn't lived much yet.
The way that we come to know God, not know about God.
You know, you can read books that will say things about God, some of which will be more
true than others, but none of which will actually let you know God.
Any more than reading a thousand magazines of articles about a celebrity will cause you
to actually know the celebrity.
You'll just know a bunch of things about them that are more or less true.
The way you come to know God is by living with God.
Right, so the way we come to understand and to know spiritual things is not by reading about them or learning them or having them demonstrated or proven to us
but by living them.
And that means entering into a way of life the kind of cycles and patterns that we've been talking about tonight in the book of Jubiles, structuring our life around God.
And around these...
cycles all of which bring us into his presence, bring us into contact with him over and over again and shape our lives.
And as we do that and as we do that over time,
we start to understand these things.
And even even in the case of like XYZ ABC,
you can talk to folks in my parish.
I'm sure in most other Orthodox parishes in the United States who came into the Orthodox church from outside.
Right, you'll find plenty of people who I didn't get that whole Mary thing and
da da da da da, right? And maybe they wanted somebody to argue them about it. They
wanted to read 20 books about it, whatever when they were coming into the church. But
what they'll actually tell you is after two years, three years, four years, five
years of being Orthodox, it just clicked one day. I just got it. It just made sense.
People don't believe things, people don't hold onto ideas or have ideas or produce ideas because they're true.
If that happened, no one would ever be wrong about anything.
Ideas become believable because they become useful in explaining our experience and in structuring our lives.
So, if you're living a very modern, very worldly, different...
way of life, then there are tons of things that the Orthodox Church has to
teach you that you will never understand from outside. You can only understand
them once you become a part of them, because being part of the community and
its way of life and those rhythms and those cycles will shape you until they
just they make sense, because you kind of live. So I think yeah we need to get
away from what we
We've been taught in terms of enlightened modernity about, you know, I understand, therefore
I can believe.
I understand, therefore I can be faithful.
Right.
And get back to your St. Augustine.
See, I'm saying all these nice things about St. Augustine, all of a sudden.
What St. Augustine actually said, which is, I am faithful so that I will understand.
Hmm.
Well Marina I hope that
that helps a little bit.
I hope that my swungering around
and your excellent insight will be a benefit
to others besides me and my foggy brain.
May it be blessed, may it be blessed.
Thank you very much for calling.
Right, Cisrism.
He truly is risen.
All right, pumpkin spice.
Oh.
You know, you didn't even say where people should send their hate mail.
I'm kind of surprised, Father.
Oh, yeah.
That's Father Andrew at ancient faith.com.
That's right.
Thank you.
I had them sending you something else.
By the way, it's coming up.
Whole Council of God here in a couple of months.
It gets real great.
I look forward to it.
Right.
Okay.
So angels and Charger various things.
What else we got in terms of fun details from the police.
We get we get it.
explicit almost greed about the calendar when it talks about actual enich.
We've talked about before on the show enich of course is the seventh from Adam as we're reminded by St. Jude.
Not coincidentally the seventh figure in the Sumerian Kings list creates the calendar.
not coincidentally,
Enoch has said to have lived 365 years.
So there is this deep association in the text of Genesis itself when you understand it in the ancient Erystin context with the cat with a calendar.
Yeah.
A solar calendar.
But here in Jubilee's that's made explicit about the 364 day Enoch calendar.
Expressely the 364 day calendar and the dangers of not following the 364 day calendar.
that was revealed through ENEC.
to the world. And again, this is a revelation. Right. So Book of Jubilee sees that calendar is being
the actual structure of a year. Right. As God created a year, which is being revealed to us
through Enic, but is built into, built into creation. And then once we get a little closer to Noah,
We get mastima.
Alright.
I mean, oh...
Yeah, not everybody's favorite devil figure.
Yeah, for a figure. He's a really interesting devil figure.
I mean, I'm not it's one of them devil figures, but yeah, yeah, he's out of all of them. He is one of them.
Yeah, that's yeah, it what's I mean, what's what's what's crazy about this devil figure is that he's human.
Basically, sort of yeah, yeah, sort of a giant.
Yeah, he's a giant. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
He's a giant.
You know, in Jubilee's, right, the way that the flood goes,
is the flood comes because of the giants.
I mean, this is in Genesis 2 as well, but it's really explicit
in Jubilee's that the flood comes to wipe out the giants,
and then they're dead, but their spirits are all there, right?
and immediately they begin to attack Noah and his sons.
And Noah basically says to God, I thought you sent the flood to deal with this problem
and here they are still attacking us, but they're just disembodied spirits.
And God, I'm paraphrasing a little bit here.
God basically says, you know you're right, I'm going to go ahead and send them all into
the abyss so they'll leave you alone.
And so then one of these spirits steps forward and this is mastima and he says, hold on.
Hold on a second Lord.
Let's make a deal.
Yeah, exactly.
could be
You can send, go ahead, send most of them down to the abyss.
But how about 10% of my boys and I get to hang out here
and we promise we're gonna afflict only the wicked.
Only the wicked.
You don't like the wicked, we don't like the wicked.
Right, exactly.
And God essentially says, okay, you have a deal,
but when the time comes, you have to go down
to the abyss with the rest, right?
So
This is this bargain that Masterma makes, right?
And now, now, Masterma is making this deal
from the demons' perspective.
This is because they're haters, right?
They just hate humans.
But the reason God agrees to the deal
is that He is going to use them afflicting the wicked
to bring the wicked to repentance.
Right. So this is because God actually loves the wicked.
Right. This is that theme of the left hand of God.
God using demonic activity to bring about His purposes.
his purposes.
namely repentance and holiness and salvation of mankind.
You know, so, so yeah, this is interesting because like in Jubilee's,
it's presented in a literal way that angels mate with humans.
I mean, go see our giant episode from way back in 2020 for the whole
nine yards about all this stuff.
A whole sorted affair.
Exactly, exactly.
But in Jubilee's, it's presented in a literal fashion that, that, that,
The following angels mate with humans.
produce giants. And so, you know, the fallen angels that do this are chained up down in
Tardarus. This parallels the whole Titan story from Greek mythology. Chained up down in Tardarus.
And so then the presence of evil spirits on the earth is dead giants. Right. So the fallen
angels are down there where they can't hurt anybody. But it's dead giants that are the
presence of that are the demon spirits roaming around
possessing people and stuff.
Right, they're the demons and the New Testament and yeah. Yeah, yeah, so and and we should just emphasize here that we're
Telling you that this is what these texts present. We're not saying that this is Christian dogma
Right, I'm not aware of any kind of it hasn't been dogmatized anywhere. Yeah, yeah now it is the pre-supposition of the New Testament
Right, it's the pre-supposition of the synoptic gospels, I should say right this adopted gospels
various ways presuppose this. You get the demons expressly act as King Jesus not to
cast them into the abyss. Asi, are you here to troll us before the time?
Right. Which that's not a reference to anything in the Old Testament.
Right. Referring to this bargain. Right. So this is, and of course this is the the Archie
right book, the origin of evil spirits.
Yeah.
that I think is still in print.
So yeah, so from the point of view of jubilee,
which is the dissertation on this.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Obviously this is an optical hospitals.
So from the point of view of jubilee's then,
this is not only the origin of evil spirits,
of demons on earth now,
but also that sort of the main devil figure
is one of these, is a dead giant.
Yeah.
Right?
Yeah, we're going to see mastima.
Do it so!
I'm pretty sure we've mentioned this before but there's a whole bunch of these devil figures.
Yeah, we should do, I think we should do an episode on Devils at some point.
So you've got, you've got a Zazel, you've got the devil, you've got the Satan, right?
shows up in joke. You've got mastima. You've got Boliol.
Right, so there's there's a bunch of these, right? And we've got all these names, no source
that you can find in Second Temple Judaism or early Christianity thinks that all of these
are separate beings. They've usually got like one or two of them and sort of all the
devil figures of the Bible are collapsed into one or two of them. Yeah. Right, so Second
knee neck, right, Azazels very clearly Azazel.
like Dave Atoneman is Azal, but he's also the serpent from the Garden of Eden.
Right, so they just kind of collapse all the devil figures into Azal.
Jubilee's collapses most of them into mastima.
Yeah.
We're gonna see how mastima shows up several more times here.
He gets up to shenanigans throughout the rest of the book of Jubilee.
Right.
So yeah, there's all.
What kind of fun stuff related to the flood here?
So right after the flood, the wicked humans have been wiped out, right?
But the giants, yeah, have been the rest of the humans for that matter.
Yeah, it's what it's family.
And yet Noah then makes this sacrifice and it says, for the land.
He atones for the land.
Yeah.
He's atone for the land.
And this fits in again with what we've talked about in terms of what atonement is you
You can go back.
those episodes, where atomina the day of atomina is made for inanimate objects, spaces and objects in the
world are atoned for. Yeah, cleaned up. And cleaned up. Pure. Right. Yeah. This is about removing. So the
giants and all those humans who are doing all those wicked evil things are gone. Now sort of he's
offering these sacrifices to sort of purify the land from like the residue or the taint of their
in their wickedness. Yeah. Yeah. Alright, so we
We promised the prayer of Noah against the demons.
So this is right before Mastima shows up and says,
I'd like to, let's make a deal.
This is when Mastima and all the,
and 100% of the dead giants are messing with him and his sons.
This is what Noah says to God.
God of the Spirit, which are in all flesh,
who has acted mercifully with me and saved me in my sons
from the water of the flood and did not let me perish
as you did the children of perdition.
Because great was your grace upon me and great.
Great was your mercy upon my soul.
Let your grace be lifted up upon my sons
and do not let the evil spirits rule over them,
lest they destroy them from the earth.
But bless me and my sons and let us grow
and increase and fill the earth.
And you know that which your watchers,
the fathers of these spirits did in my days
and also these spirits who are alive,
shut them up and take them to the place of judgment
and do not let them cause corruption
among the sons of your servant, oh my God,
because they are cruel and recreated to destroy.
Let them not rule.
over the spirits of the living because you alone know their judgment and do not let them
have power over the children of the righteous, henceforth, and forever.
So that's Noah's exorcism prayer, basically.
Prayer of protection against demons.
Yeah.
And as we mentioned, right, that God of spirits involved flesh was at the beginning of
this, in which we pray in the memorial, it's not, the memorial is not just sort of borrowing
that phrase. The Association of Praying for the Departed
and especially at a funeral with exorcism, with warding off demons, that's totally a thing.
Yes.
Yeah.
There's toll house people out there getting super excited.
But the same kind of excitement is with giants though.
It's a lot less joyful.
But notice, right, notice also what these spirits are about.
They're out destroying humanity.
Yeah.
Huh, right. They're about just
that's a view of Jubilee's, that's a view of the scriptures about these demonic spirits,
even the ones that are worshipped as gods by the nations.
These aren't quote-unquote competing religions.
The value of the same thing.
This is spirits that want to destroy humanity.
And so converting someone from paganism to Christianity is
is saving them. That's why we use that word. Yeah. It's not saving them from God being angry
at them. Yeah. God loves them. It's saving them from the demons who have control of them
and want to destroy them. Yeah. Saying them free from slavery. Yes. As we mentioned,
it's also Noah who starts the feast of weeks who starts celebrating pedicost, but that's
the giving of the car
covenant with him. So the covenant with Noah is sort of this pre-participation in the
eternal reality of the covenant with Moses, as Jubilee presents it. It also
fleshes out the figure of Canaan, like Ham's descendant. Interestingly, it spells
Canaan not the way it's spelled in Genesis.
with two A's. It spells it C-A-I-N-A-N, roughly, meaning it's like cane is in cane and
able. Yeah, it's a little bit more.
A little cane.
Cainin is the new cane. Yeah. So then he's deliberately recast as another cane, right,
after the flood. Right. So cane touches off in his genealogy, this whole descent to the
the giants, the Nephilim and the Flood, right?
And then, well, wait, there's giants after the flood.
There's all this other stuff that goes down in the Torah and the book of Joshua, right?
Even leading up to the Tower of Babel, well,
Cainin is the new Cain in the sense that he's the one who does this.
And in Jubilee, he does it in a very literal way.
Cainin is taught how to read,
and he goes and he discovers these inscriptions made in stone
in certain mountains, right?
and this is probably a reference by
Jubilee's to the kind of mountain carving that the Persian Empire did since this is the most
exilic text but he finds all of this stuff written in stone on these mountains from before the flood
right it's written in stone that's how it survived the flood right on the mountains and it's all the
stuff the watchers taught humanity so he rediscoveres it can't rediscover it he goes and builds a city and
He builds his city.
He has a dissident named Ur, which is kind of on the nose.
Sids Ur is the Sumerian word for city
And was of course the name of the city of Ur that Abraham came from but Ur goes and builds the city of Ur
that's in Jubilee's and
That whole narrative then culminates in the Tower of Babel and the Tower of Babel in Shinar
According to Jubilee's is between Asher and Babylon
Yeah
again as an anachronism, right? But it's a between the capital of the Assyrians and the capital
of the Babylonians, right? The great enemies of Israel later, right? So the idea is this whole Mesopotamian
tradition, Babylon, Asher, Uruk, all of this is all being sort of bald together here as coming from
Cainin who's the new Cain and recreates this
situation of giants of the claim to have these antideleuvian secrets all of that.
It's bundled into this figure of Canaan.
Also with Noah and his sons, the world gets apportioned by God to Noah and his sons.
Hmm so
For the perspective of this it's not just like right we get
And yet in in Deuteronomy chapter two, we get that, right,
okay, Israel is gonna have this piece of land
and Edom's gonna have this piece of land,
like the descendants of Abraham.
But Jubilee's pulls this back to Noah and says,
no, God gives like Europe and Asia really to
Japheth's children and Africa to Ham's children
and the Middle East essentially to Shem's children.
to Sham's Shelver.
So all of them are
sort of given these land allotments by God. Israel is called eventually to this very special
role in terms of the nations. But the rest of the nations are to follow. This is the first place
where you get what becomes prominent in Jewish tradition later, including rabbinic Jewish tradition,
the idea of the Noahide laws, where again in Jubilee's, the commandments we've talked about,
the ones that apply not just to
Jewish people, but also to Gentiles from like Leviticus and other places. Those get extracted
and pushed back here to Noah. So those are commandments that are part of the covenant
with Noah that are given to all of his sons, whereas the Torah then is later given to Israel
in particular. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And so the rest of the nations are responsible to follow
those those was but that
where they get associated with Noah, at least in our first extant text is here in Jubilee's.
The Tower of Babel gets blown down by a great wind in Jubilee's 10 vs 26.
Right. There's not a lot of Tower of Babel stuff in Jubilee's. It tells the story very briefly.
but it does have to think that had
listened to Ricky Rohan.
And all his nonsense.
Yeah, there's not a lot in terms of text.
Jubilee is about the tower, but it does have this cool detail of it being blown over by
a great wind, which is against not in Genesis, but is echoed in acts with the coming of
Holy Spirit with this great wind and
But liturgically, Pentecost is the undoing of Bable, right?
So there's this Pentecostal character going on here.
And so in sense of a great wind coming to blow over the Tower of Bable, it's sort of
a, you know, a, a both now and not yet on some level of the coming of the Holy Spirit
of Pentecost, you know, it's God who descends and brings this and expressed here as a great
So it's just kind of a fun detail. It's just sort of mentioned there very briefly, but it is it is there
Yeah, so let's do more mastima stuff
Yeah, so
mastima shows up again in the story of Abraham. Yes. Yeah
He shows up
At the time Abraham's father is Tara is born. Yes, he sends and I love this in the text a devastation of crows
How many crows do you have to have to have a devastation of crows?
I don't know.
And they come and they just have two or three, it's an attempted murder.
There you go, that's true.
But yeah, they come in the reason why they're called a devastation is because when the
farmers are planting all their seeds, the crows come and eat the seeds and snatch them
away.
And so this brings a famine, right?
So number one, fun parallel with the parable of the sower, right?
You know, the enemy can snatch them.
and take away the things that's the devil coming into.
in a way that yeah exactly exactly but then there's all these cool details about the youth of
Abraham. Well he's still Abraham at this point. So yeah it becomes clear early on that Abraham
realizes that he's surnabied by a dollar and is totally against that and he goes out and he
drives away the crows and not only does he drive away the crows from around you know his family
but he like people kind of ask him to come and do the same for them and so he gets to know
is this sort of pro-exorcist. And there's this growing theme of Abram being against idolatry
and being anti- idolatry. And even at one point going to his dad and saying, you know, shouldn't we
only be worshiping Yahweh and his dad saying, well, they'll talk badly about me, you know, if I'm not
an idolater or whatever. And then there's this really fascinating bit where Abram has shown
Hebrew
Of course, no one knows Hebrew by this point, which Jubilee says is the language of creation.
Yeah.
And I mean, there's some, I don't think it's in Jubilee's, but there's some traditions
about Hebrew being the language that everyone speaks before Bable.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's to be the original, the original language.
You know.
And then so what happens is that...
That's exactly true, but...
Right.
That God shows him how to read Hebrew.
he's able to gain, you know, not...
of God from doing so there's this whole arc of Abram being the guy who's going to bring
his anti- idolatry and so he's going to sort of lead the way out of idolatry. Is this
cool theme that's in the Abraham stuff there? And Massimus shows up a lot as kind of his adversary.
Namaste. Yeah. Massimus shows up again. So before the whole episode of the Sacrifice of Isaac,
Master of the show.
up and it's seen very reminiscent of the beginning of the book of Job. Yeah. Where Master
was shows up before God and says, Hey, consider your servant Abraham. He really loves that
Isaac kid. I bet you if you did something to that Isaac kid, he'd turn on you. And
so this scene is added to explain why God told Abraham to go sacrifice Isaac. It was like,
sort of like with Job to prove a point to, in this case,
mastima.
So, Massdema here is sort of cast as the Satan from Job.
And yeah, so Massd was kind of lurking around.
And he's feeling if you compare this to other second temple literature that we haven't talked about in detail on the show yet.
Usually this role, bothering Abraham is his asal.
So there's a sense in which mastima and Azazel are here getting kind of smushed even though the name Azazel doesn't occur.
if you're familiar with some of the other literature.
Yeah, yeah.
So another detail that I just thought was kind of cool,
not just because it mentions mastima,
but I don't know, I liked this.
So when Jacob is born, in Book of Jubilee's,
Abraham is still alive, even though that's his grandson
and he actually then goes to bless his grandson
and this isn't Jubilee's chapter 19.
He says, and may the spirit of man.
not rule over you or over your seed in order to remove you from following the Lord who is your God henceforth and forever.
And may the Lord God be for you and for the people of Father always and may you be a firstborn son, go my son and peace.
So it functions in a little ways as a kind of prophecy of Jacob becoming the firstborn even though he's not the firstborn.
You know, here as well.
It presents that is, see by presenting Abraham is blessing him, that makes it a little
more legitimate seeming that him getting the birthright through trickery, which is what's
in the actual book of Genesis.
Yeah.
Fun.
When Abraham eventually dies, he gives sort of a mini testament.
It's pretty short, but you get sort of his last words.
And the important theme there, because we see this in a lot of anachic literature, is that
In the future there is
going to be some super wicked generation that's going to proceed the coming of the Messiah
and the deliverance of the people the same way and that's paralleled with the generation
of Noah's Day that was wiped out.
They're going to be wicked like that right before the coming of the Messiah and the end of
things in the final judgment. God's going to interview
at that point and that's just a running theme in anachic literature. And we see that crop up a lot,
especially in the synoptic gospels, but other places in the New Testament, right? When Christ
talks about how long will I tolerate this wicked and perverse generation? That idea of the wicked and
perverse generation comes from anachic literature like this. He's referencing this as like that
generation that's like the generation of Noah or when he talks about the
days of the Son of Man being like the days of Noah when people are being married and given in marriage.
And then judgment came upon them suddenly, right? That whole comparison, that whole set of ideas,
we see all through an ockic literature, but also here in Jubilee's in sort of Abraham's dying words.
Yeah, so there's one other bit about Massimo that I wanted to mention, because again,
Again this is a fun kind of retconning, I don't know.
of a very familiar story from the scripture.
And this is actually not Genesis, this is Exodus,
this is the beginning of Exodus.
As we said, Jubilee presents the history kind of up
to Moses on Sinai.
So you're going to have some Exodus stuff there too.
So Massimo gets involved in Exodus.
Early on, Massimo tries to kill Moses.
And because Moses is going to lead his people out of Egypt,
and so mass with
trying to prevent that from happening. And God has said to bind Massima to prevent that from
happening, to prevent him from killing Moses so that the Exodus can happen, right? What's
interesting then also is, you know, when the showdown begins with Pharaoh, it actually says that
Massima is loose. And the reason why he's loose again is basically to allow him to participate
with Pharaoh and the Egyptians in pursuing Israel. So there's this idea that
demonic power is what is pursuing Israel, right? So it's not just Pharaoh and, you know,
the Egyptians. It's, well, in this case, as it says in Exodus, the gods of Egypt. So
Massimus depicted essentially as one of the gods of Egypt in this case, or the god of Egypt
really. And then, and then when it comes time for the first born to be killed at the Passover
itself. It says that the
powers of mastima are released to kill the firstborn. And so the image of that we would often
describe as the angel of death is associated with this figure of mastima. So there's he's participating
kind of all this demonic sort of activity that's related to the Exodus. So a really interesting
angle, a really, really interesting angle. Right. Yeah. And you can see the pattern there too of
God sort of having him on the leash, right? He can't act.
act against God's will, but God occasionally setting him loose why as a judgment, right,
to judge the wicked, right?
God removes that restraint at times.
Yeah, and there's a couple of other little details that are kind of interesting.
We talked last time in the testament of Levi about how sort of priesthood was projected back
on to the figure of Levi, right? The...
person. And that's here in the book of Jubilee's also Levi because of his zeal in defending
the honor of his sister and killing all the men of Shackham receives priesthood as a reward.
And also there's some interesting things with you know in the text of Genesis of course
He saw as like, it's up being the good guy.
in the story if you actually read it, sorry Cali.
Right.
But at Esau and Jacob Reckenshile and everything,
and everything's fine, and the Edomites are even fine
in Judah, on to me too.
And it's only later when Edom rebels against Judah
at the time that Judah is going into exile,
that's where everything goes wrong in terms of Edom,
That's what...
when God says, eat him, he has hated.
And so that gets sort of pushed back
for the perspective of the author,
back in the Genesis where after Esau kind of has made peace
with and forgiven Jacob, Esau's sons, his descendants,
his sons and grandsons are really ticked about it,
decide, you know, Esau's a woose.
Right, we're doing that.
And so they go and start attacking Jacob and Jacob's family.
And that's the way of sort of projecting that.
Like yeah, you saw was okay,
but his descendants were a problem, right?
But that gets kind of retrojected back into
yeah, into Genesis itself.
Earlier generations, yeah.
In that way, yeah.
So well, that wraps up our kind of bonus round.
round. I don't know if some interesting
details in the book of Jubilee is that both of us wanted to talk about. I wanted to just
talk here at the end a little bit about apocrypha in general. I know we've done that a lot, but
particularly in terms of this book because it would be tempting to read this and say, oh,
this is the real story of Genesis and early Exodus. And then some people might hear this
Let's see, wait a minute.
am I supposed to believe all this? That's what really happened. And especially the stuff that
my trip people up is like the origins of evil spirits and all this kind of stuff. And I know that
particularly, like this show, we talk a lot about a lot of kinds of details and things that
that are probably new to a lot of people.
And so there can be a feeling of let me get hold of all of this knowledge.
And some people really embrace that idea and some people are like,
oh, this is all very dangerous, you know, that kind of thing.
And I think that that, and this kind of connects a little bit with what,
what father you were saying to our second caller to Marine.
It can get us into that area of treating these things like their pieces of data.
you know that you need to get right or needs to be rejected or whatever.
might be. But I think that we have to remember what it is that apocrypha are. Right? So these are
texts that are not read out loud in church as scripture. Again, there is the exception of the Ethiopian
tradition. But I'll be willing to guess that the vast majority of our listeners are not from that
that tradition.
And so that this is not a canonical text for most of them.
This is an apocryphal text.
And the text like this are useful to read at home,
or you know, useful to talk about on podcasts.
Meaning that they're not to be taken in the same way
with the same kind of authority as scripture.
It's something less, something lower, right?
And we have to sift them according
to the larger tradition of the church.
Some of the sifting will be things will say, well, you know, that's just not consistent with the rest of the Church and the Church, we're just going to leave that alone.
Others will be, we, things we can say, well, that's an interesting take on that.
You know, that's nice.
Other things will be, will provide us with very deep kinds of insight and context for the Scriptures and for the tradition of the Church.
Like a great example being that prayer that's used against
demons by Noah, then we use in praying for our departed because the idea is we don't want them
to be attacked by dark spirits, you know, in the passage from this life into the next, you know,
keep away, right? So, so I think the thing we have to remember, and this is a theme throughout
all the stuff we've done in this podcast now for almost four years. Man, it's hard to believe
but almost four years. This is episode 92 everyone by the way.
is that the point of all of this is not to create a big stack of weird things to
believe or teach or whatever. That's not the point at all. The point is to find in
this the ways that we can become more faithful, right, in the ways that we can
become saints, the ways that we can become holy ones, right? And for me what
Jubilee's does it
is because it kind of attempts to pull back the veil
in a way that's a little bit more explicit
than the canonical scriptures.
Pull back the veil on the unseen world
of the spiritual realities behind things.
I think that it helps to give us a better habits of mind
when it comes to understanding what is in the scriptures
and to understanding what is in these more sort
central position.
in Christian tradition, right?
That it gives us habits of thought, it gives us,
I don't know, I think the word taste might be a good one.
It gives us a taste and not just in terms of like,
meaning a sample, but taste in the sense of,
my tastes are formed in such a way that I can recognize
and understand things that maybe were not
as recognizable or understandable to me before.
because we get a stronger feeling for what the world of ancient people was like,
what the ancient Near East was like, and what their spiritual neighborhood was like.
And I think that Jubilee's is a great text for a lot of those things all together,
because it's very clearly apocryphal, it's not Scripture.
But it's also very clearly engaging with Scripture.
That's its real purpose, is its engaging with what's in the scripture.
It's giving us the author's thoughts and understandings and collections of traditions regarding what is in the scripture.
And so it helps to train us.
I think that's probably the greatest value in this text.
It trains us of how to approach the Christian tradition in a way that's going to be God willing more, Selvek for us,
And also for those with whom we interact, that we become more
more saintly people, that's really the whole point of it, to draw closer to Christ, to
become more like Christ, to become, as the Lord says, in the Gospel of Luke equal to the
angels. And I think this text is great for all of that. So, Father Stephen, your final thoughts
on this?
So Aristotle was right that we are what we repeatedly do.
We tend to look at the way we structure our lives and time and the calendar.
It's kind of indifferent. It's kind of unimportant. Right? When we think about what we do or even what we repeatedly do,
we don't tend to think of it in those terms,
terms of cycles and patterns and the calendar, the way we organize our days and our weeks and our months and our years.
We tend to think about it just in terms of AC.
like good deeds, bad deeds, good things we do, bad things we do.
I'm a good person because I do good things.
That person's a bad person because they do bad things.
But what Aristotle is actually talking about,
and what Jubilee's is so focused on
is exactly that kind of structuring.
There's a period of my life in junior high
where I basically live from New Comic Day to New Comic.
day. And Frederick Wardam was right. It turned me into a juvenile delinquent.
Somewhat literally. But you know there have been other periods of my life where I
lived paycheck to paycheck. I lived summer to summer if you're in school or
teaching school, birthday to birthday, take your pick.
And all of those things will shape you.
They'll shape how you see yourself, how you understand who you are, how you relate to
a community, if you're even part of one, right?
Because part of what constitutes a community, part of what makes a community a community.
Not in the sense of this is when you can accurately apply that label, but in the sense of what
actually call
causes a group of human persons to function together as a community is that you have a shared rhythm of life.
That you share in these patterns of life together.
That's part of what binds you together and makes you actually a community is that you're all being shaped together and drawn together by following this.
So if you pick something that's just your own you're not good it's not gonna draw you together into any kind of
community at all. But whatever it is, it will shape you, it will change you. It will
change how you see the world, how you experience life in the world, how you experience other
people, how you experience your own interiority, how you think of and experience God. All of
those things will be shaped. All of those things will be shaped. And this is why at the core
What Christianity is, is a way of life, and that way of life is made up of these patterns of life.
Of a weekly cycle that culminates in the celebration of Christ's resurrection on Sunday.
A yearly cycle that culminates in the celebration of Paska.
Christ's resurrection, not a particular Sunday.
of the cycle of the rest of the feast, of cycles both weekly and yearly.
of fasting and of feasting. And by the way, by the way, the feasting is more important.
I'm just going to blow some Orthodox people's heads off. I don't care.
The feasting we're doing right now to celebrate Christ's resurrection after Paska is more
important than the fasting we did during Lent. You want my evidence? What separated Orthodox Christians
from Nostics, from Manicians, from Ench...
grittites from almost all the heretics of the ancient world was not fasting. They all
fasted. They all fasted to a greater extreme than Christians did. What separated the Christians
from all of them is that the Christians feast. The Christians have times of the year where
they enjoy and exult in and receive joy from and give thanks to God for
all the good things of his creation. They actually got married and had children.
They didn't all practice celibacy, the actual Christians. So we need to remember
that. I think we need to keep that in perspective. But there are times of
feasting and times of fasting. And it's not that the fasting is
It's unimportant, just the feasting is kind of more important.
Giving
thanks to God for his creation and his world.
But those cycles, they change us in a good way.
They mold us.
They help us as we were saying earlier.
Come to know God.
Not just know things about Him.
Not just be able to win arguments about His attributes on the Internet.
But actually know Him.
And be known by Him.
And be transformed by that.
be drawn together into community that's
practicing those same cycles so that we have not just other people who we go to
the same venue with once a week or so but actual brothers and sisters.
Actual friends, actual people who we share our lives with. Right? That's how it
happens. It happens through these simple things of how do I structure my...
week around most of the time two fast days, a couple days where I go to church, five or
so days where I work, right? Time I spend with my family, time I spend on other things.
In this regular cycle, week after week, right? We have to leave the mountain after liturgy,
Right, but we come back to it. We come back into the presence of God.
We have the leaf-taking of Paska, but then the next year we come back to it.
Over and over and over again.
And the eternal realities of God become more and more part of our life, every cycle, every
time around the bend.
All building to that day when we leave this life and all of those eternal realities Lord
willing become our
eternal realities. Become the realities in which we live our eternal life. So those are my thoughts.
Amen. Amen. Well, that's our show for tonight everybody. Thank you very much for listening for joining us.
If you didn't call us live, you didn't listen to us live. We'd still like to hear from you. You can
email us at LordofSpeertsNationFate.com. You can message us at our Facebook page. You can also
Let's leave us a voice mail and speak, Paid, Done.
comms, Les Flores, spirits. And if you have any basic questions about orthodox
Christianity, or you need help finding a parish, head over to orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast of the second and fourth Thursdays of the
month at 7 PM Eastern 4 PM Pacific. If you want to make a podcast like this,
you can learn how to on Skillshare, who doesn't sponsor us, but I'd love to take
their money. If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page on our discussion
group. Please rate and review this podcast to help share with other
and also please recommend it directly to your friends and family that are going to benefit from it.
Finally, be sure to go to www.extrapaste.com.stokesupport and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
And if you need a lawyer, call the Eagle team.
I don't even know the legal eagle guy's real name. You could go to his channel and figure out how to do that.
But I'll take his money too.
Thank you, good night.
And my God bless you all.
Christ is risen.
He truly is risen.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father.
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 and thousands of thousands, saying with
a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation.
chapter